All right.
Hey, GM, GM, everybody.
Thank you for joining us and welcome to Meta 511, an NFT
panel discussion on crypto art and one of ones.
A huge thank you to our host, Yoonik, for including the session
in their ongoing series on web 3.
I'm pleased to be joined by Sasha Styles, Claire Silver, Ina
Moja, and Sam Strad.
But before we get started, OK, there's a bit of lag here,
but we're going to try laboring on.
So first of all, a reminder.
OK.
All right, let's give this a shot again.
So reminder, if you're attending,
you can ask questions in the on chat or on Twitter
using hashtag NFT Q&A. So the topic of today
is really around crypto art and one of ones.
And why is this topic important?
And one of ones are the NFT equivalent
of a unique painting or photograph.
They're usually owned by a single individual.
Placing of one of one with a notable collector
institution or fund in the NFT world
is as important as it is with works
in the traditional art world.
So provenance and provability often
become a very important aspect.
And especially when you play that to the digital world,
you have provability and you also
have the provable scarcity aspect.
And a classic case in the traditional world
would be the Salva Carmundi by Leonardo da Vinci,
supposedly by Leonardo, which sold as high as $450 million.
But if you look at the initial certification,
it was done by a world-renowned gallery.
But again, it shows you that it is an imprecise art at best.
And that's where the blockchain comes into be.
So I'm very, very happy and thrilled to be here
with four tremendous guests.
Sam Spratt, Sasha Styles, Claire Silver, Inamoja.
And we're going to get into a little bit of the discussion
on why one of one art is relevant.
But before we do that, I'd like each of them
to introduce themselves and maybe spend two to three minutes
kind of introducing a little bit about who they are.
So I'm going to start with Claire.
Claire, why don't you start and kick us off here.
Hey, good morning.
I will do my best to do that.
Hope everybody is having a great day.
I'm Claire Silver.
I'm an AI collaborative artist.
And I do a lot of work with exhibitions
and sort of curating contests for AI art
and hoping people sort of push the boundaries
into other mediums, like film, video games, music, et cetera.
Very exciting time to be working with AI as an artist.
And I'm also a co-founder of A2, which
is a collective for emerging artists
to help get them some visibility.
We did an exhibition of their work at Basel last year
and won in New York as well.
So that's me.
Hey, thanks, Claire.
You know, over to you.
I'm with the one.
I'm Ina Moja.
I'm a visual cook-green, which is a three-for-good organization.
Thanks, Ina.
Sasha, over to you.
Hi.
I'm actually going to break the trend
and put my camera on to say hi to everyone.
Thanks so much for having all of us here.
This is a really wonderful group.
So just by way of a quick introduction,
again, my name is Sasha.
I'm a first-generation, comic, Mongolian-American poet,
an artist, as well as an AI researcher.
And I work mainly at the intersection of text and technology.
I'm a lifelong writer and poet.
And really, my main areas of focus these days
are generative literature and language art,
and, of course, blockchain and poetics.
I'm particularly interested in the resonances
between poetry and technology and considering poetry as code.
Poetry is a kind of ancient data storage system.
Along with all the conceptual implications
that poetry can bring into this web3 world of digital ownership
and provenance and preservation.
In 2021, I actually published my first book, which
is a collection of hybrid poetry and artwork.
And it's called technology.
And I actually have it right here.
And it's all about what it means to be human in a nearly post-human era.
And I wrote this book with a non-human co-author, an AI-powered
alter-ego, a text generator, rooted in GPT-2 and GPT-3,
just an ancestor of chat GPT, who's
been getting a lot of attention lately.
And I've been working with this text generator
and customizing it since 2018.
I am very grateful to say that technology, my book,
has been praised and welcomed not just by poets,
but also by the tech community and the AI world
and by futurists and visionaries, such as Ray Kurtzpile, which
has really meant a lot to me.
I am very wedded to physical books as a lifelong writer.
Books are very near and dear to me.
But I'm also very interested in publishing innovations,
and especially what web3 promises for writers like myself, not
just artists, but writers and poets.
And I'm very interested in looking
at how I can use blockchain, protocol, and different mediums
to manifest my poetry in different ways.
And I've had a lot of fun over the past few years
getting to publish my poems in various experimental formats
by places like FXHASH and PONTOM and 50 Gateway,
and objects.
And I even sold an AI-powered poem last year at Christie's,
which still is sort of unbelievable to me.
And last but not least, I wanted to just say that I am also
co-founder of a group called Diverseverse, which
is a literary gallery dedicated to crypto poetry and really
NFT literature at large.
We are dedicated to exploring the ideas that poetry is art,
that poetry is also a technology.
And that language really shouldn't have any limits
or any boundaries.
And we've been working on a lot of really exciting projects
that are coming up this year, which I'm excited to share.
Thanks.
Thank you, Sasha.
Sam, last but not least.
Hey, good morning, everyone.
Man, thank you for having us.
This is really special.
Bharat, really good to be with you.
And all three of you are just extremely talented and thoughtful
women.
It's an honor to be alongside you.
I started out as an oil painter.
And I would study the technique of the old master's
feet of horror Rubens.
But around 12 years ago, I discovered
a digital tablet.
And then I pretty much spent the rest of the time from then
until now, trying to figure out how
I take the warmth, the flaws, the attempt of the medium
that I started with, and how to translate it
into this space that we actually use and operate
primarily today.
My early gigs were a staff illustrator for tech blogs.
I was making 20 bucks in illustration.
I transitioned that into a pretty solid career
doing album covers for Kid Cudi, You've Done a Glover,
Logic, working on games like Borderlands and Red Dead
Redemption.
But in that arc, in that 10 years that I
was spent building this, I was creating other people's worlds.
And a few years ago, I had this very fascinating,
but honestly, rather brutal series of events
kind of unseat me, untether me from that process.
I noticed that in creating all of this and stacking
a client list and chasing the commissions from each of them,
that I had become rather abstracted
from the idea of what an artist is supposed to be.
And there is this strange sense of decay
in that of this prior iteration that I had spent and dedicated
my whole life to.
And there was something a few years ago
that in me, I felt I got to make my own world.
I have to say my own thing.
I had lived this path of a mimic, almost,
of being the kind of person or artist I needed to be for every job
or project or artist that came my way.
And something about this space when I started creating
my series, Lucy, felt like, oh my god, everyone else
is doing this too.
They all have their own version of it,
whatever kind of person they are.
It doesn't matter if they're an artist or a collector
or a platform builder or an engineer.
There's a lot of people here who felt that sense of decay.
Like they were missing the growth part of life.
They were in the dissociative part of it.
And Lucy, the series of episodic paintings
that I've created is about that.
It's about taking our first steps again of trying anew.
And within this, I think there's something
about 101 art in particular that I feel
I spent my whole life trying to make covers and facades
and advertisements that would pop off the shelf
to try to grab as many people as possible through their noise.
And in that process, I was very alone, very isolated,
trying to do that.
And here, there's none of that during this year
that I studied this space.
I've just been creating.
We get to kind of just do as we please make what we feel.
And these feelings, no matter how over earnest or melodramatic,
only a single person needs to see it.
That's one of one.
It's person to person.
Only a single individual needs to feel the frequency
that you're on.
From my 10 years of a career, that is such a powerful seismic
shift in how I create and how I deliver art.
Where a 101 piece of art is capable of holding a rather sacred
bond that this individual story and the source of it
can kind of stack or multiply across the ledger
as other people bid on it and gets eventually collected
by another individual.
There's a story right in that.
But it's once that individual thing
has transferred that the soloed-off atomized portion of it
starts becoming collective.
That the collector can kind of breathe new life through it,
evangelize it, spread it, meme it, elevate it in a way,
far beyond the source of its own creation.
Your work starts to collide and curate alongside other artists,
like everyone here on the stage.
The medium starts to blend and overlap.
And yet, we as individuals are still
like codified on chain back to our origin points.
I love that.
I can't really begin to express how powerful that has been
over the last year of creating this project.
That freedom of movement to remove
these increments that separate what I think in the past
maybe seemed disparate elements of humanity.
Just don't feel like that here.
It's a playground to kind of tap into who you are,
but also see what you can become when you start playing together.
It's amazing.
Hey, thanks, Sam.
Hey, I want to stick with you for a second, right?
Could you tell us a little bit more about Lucy's backstory
or the origin story, if you would,
and how alternate reality shaped the body of work?
Maybe give us a little bit more of that sort of parallel universe
as you see it and how that sort of plays a part in your artwork.
Yeah, absolutely.
So Lucy was really born from this catalytic series
of events in my own life that all kind of happened simultaneously
three or four years ago.
This was in depth, some relationships ending
that distasteed my own path as an artist that I mentioned,
that feeling of waking up from a haze of something
that maybe barely rhymes with life,
both in art and itself.
I discussed about as many aspects as you could imagine
in my work, in my actions, in my knowledge, in my appearance.
I was a very sad stack at this point in time,
had a lot of feelings.
But I think I needed that violence.
And as I began regaining my footing,
I was looking for answers and that came in the form of reading
as many great stories and novels as possible.
Seeing how these things connected to each other,
going back in time and starting to see truths in the most recent ones
that were found and older ones that were found in the most ancient ones,
these questions that I'd been asking myself now,
after everything unraveled, were asked and answered like millions of times
over thousands of years.
And so I would be journaling my own wanders, my own lives,
and I would see the same thing happening in books,
rhyming patterns of both my successes, but also my failures.
And the thing that got me stuck in a more dissociative cycle for a while,
that I started to see this space really unlocked to when you put discipline
towards bending your own arc, to taking ownership agency over your own actions,
it starts to pull you out of it.
And Lucy making these paintings,
they are markers.
They're like markers of progress about the discovery of not being alone
as you try to regain your footing.
And I guess just as much so, they're like markers of our narrative of progress,
of the moments and the story that were like right for ourselves,
if I had managed to live my whole life and absolutely miss so many things,
maybe I'm a little bit of a dishonest narrator for myself,
and that it might be rather interesting if reality starts being
others around us reflecting back at us to make something that feels more solid.
And that feeling that I think Lucy came from is what I've witnessed
across pretty much every person I've come to meet and know and even love
and appreciate in this space, like Lucy, each one of these paintings
is like a carefully crafted joke at my own expense.
And they pull from prominent origin, salamat of teachings, modern day New York,
but it's mostly just when you start alone, it's not real.
It only gets real when you start bouncing off everyone else.
I love that Sam.
So art imitating life at its truest sense.
Hey, Claire, let me shift over to you.
You've described yourself as a collaborative AI artist.
Tell us about the impact of AI on your work.
I know you've got a tremendous body of work.
You've been an evangelist for AI art for as long as I can remember,
but would love to get your point of view and perspective.
Yeah, totally.
Well, so the impact of AI on my work, gosh, there's a lot.
One of the first things it did was it inspired me with questions
of what it means to be human and what art is.
Those were sort of the first.
And also, this is pretty common knowledge, but I have a chronic illness.
And so thinking about AI solving for some of those issues that humanities had forever,
like chronic illnesses, et cetera, and what we might celebrate when those parts of the
hero's journey are overcome, so to speak, what other things we might find to tell stories
about and celebrate fascinated me.
So I've been able to use AI to explore those questions in a way that I don't think I would
have necessarily been able to do alone.
And then it also augments skill, which allows me to better represent those ideas in questions,
I think, feel a lot freer.
So it's a lot like, feels like play in a way, feels like freedom of exploration, like when
you were a kid, you know, it's something I haven't experienced since then outside of
this.
So maybe why I'm such an evangelist.
I also think, you know, speaking of collaborative, it reflects what you ask for.
So if you ask for something very simple and generic, that's what it'll give you.
I try to ask it for kind of abstract notions of connection, and it gives that to me.
So it feels a lot like talking to a friend for me, collaborative, right?
Feels like talking to a friend that never gets tired of talking to you and learns you
better with every word that you speak to it.
So it does feel collaborative.
And it also encourages me to learn more because my prompting utilizes a lot of art terminology
and art history.
For example, using luminism as an art movement in the work will change the aesthetic.
If you mix up a bunch of other prompts, you can combine all of these disparate ideas into
something that feels really new.
And so I've had to learn a lot more of that.
And then photography, learning lenses and apertures and shutter speeds and lighting conditions and
then mixing all of those into a prompt.
It's really encouraged me to go deeper.
And then, yeah, lastly, I'd say it's helped me know myself a lot better too because with
AI, as you know, you can iterate a huge body of work very quickly.
So I've created hundreds of thousands of pieces over the course of, let's say a year.
I've been doing this for a few years, but I'll curate it down to five or so to share
and maybe one to mint every three months or less.
And so you really develop your taste, you really develop your aesthetic, your motifs,
your patterns, your symbols, you figure yourself out with it.
And I don't think that I would have done that either without using AI in my work.
So I think it's made me a better NFT artist as well because the ones you resonate with
most and it's hard when you have a huge body of work to know what you're going to do with
that scarce opportunity.
So I feel like it's helped me know myself more as well.
Thank you, Claire.
For those of you who don't know, Claire is my AI whisperer.
So when I'm trying to create with my two left-thumbs prompt-generated art, she is someone
I bounce my ideas off of.
But hey, let's shift over to you.
Your work is at the intersection of societal consciousness and digital art, which I think
is a very interesting sort of crossover area.
Could you tell us a bit more about Code Green and how that impacts your work as an artist?
Yes, absolutely.
So we funded Code Green.
We started working on it in early 2021 and it took us a whole year before we launched
it because I'm a traditional activist.
And so I wanted, I saw the blockchain as this incredible way to disrupt traditional philanthropy.
And our aim is to use the power of art and, you know, what, and tech to engage people
in taking actions for either the planet or having an impact.
And so for me as an artist, I've been using my voice for social gender and climate justice
for the past 15 years and my art has always been intertwined with my activism.
And either my photography, my films or my music, I always try to share messages that
to be a messenger, to speak for people who doesn't, whose voice doesn't resonate as far
as mine could.
And so when we started this, as an artist, I saw the space as something remarkably innovative
and giving the power to artists is giving the power to the space to create an incredible
shift because our artists have always been tied to the biggest revolutions and evolution
of humanity.
And so for me, I felt like, okay, I have two hats and what I'm going to be doing in here
because as an artist, I can share my art and experiment with the technology.
But as an activist and a builder, I could really create a movement that goes beyond the space
and that bridges a gap with the digital community and real life community all over, around the
world.
So what we do is we create a link between collectors, communities, artists and builders
with different SDGs action.
So we partnered with the UN SDG to do that and support the 17 SDGs and just try to make
the world a better space.
This is something that is not rooted in naivete or, you know, I'm not naive from where I
come from.
I know that working in some type of way can get you some places and that there is hope
if you build and build and believe in what you're doing.
And so it took me a whole year before sharing my minting, my first artwork because I was
busy building this good green and trying to create something that was not really in the
space and was not really what I was doing outside of the space.
So I had to find a balance experiment with different things.
And after a year we donated over two million dollars to organizations and people and really
making an impact but also bringing awareness and showing people in the web three space
that your voice count and that you can as an individual make a strong impact and have a
say in what is happening in the world and also that's what the shift in governance means
to me.
And so yeah, it has been a very exciting and rewarding experience and learning as well.
Thank you, you know.
I love the tagline from your website, right?
So the digital revolution for social evolution.
I think that's super powerful.
So thanks for that.
And hey, Sasha, over to you.
You've been described as a transhuman artist and an AI empowered poet, right?
Can you tell us and double click on Metapoetry?
Yeah, absolutely.
And by the way, I'm just sitting here so fascinated by what everyone's been saying.
I feel so grateful to get to hear more about the really beautiful practices and thought
processes behind what you're all doing.
So yes, my Metapoetry.
Well, as I said before, I've been writing my entire life and I started writing in a little
bit more of a traditional sense, but I think that's evolved really over time.
I've always been really interested, I think, fundamentally in the idea of something called
the R's Poetica.
So literally R's Poetica translates to the art of poetry.
It's this consideration of poetry as an art form.
And in terms of genre, R's Poetica is actually formally about poems that are exploring the
role of poetry and poets in society.
They're poems that are really about the poet's relationship to language, the poet's relationship
to the act of writing.
And to me, I just find this so deeply, deeply fascinating from a conceptual point of view.
And it's just fun for me to think about the idea of poetry that is self-aware or poetry
that is about poetry.
I think there's a lot that really intrigues me about that and relates to meta in a way
that I'll get to in a second.
But my first sustained project in this area was actually something called R's Poetica
Cybernetica.
So looking at poetry not just as an art form, but as a technological invention, kind of
like bringing together R's Poetica and R's Technica in the way.
And thinking through the poetics of networked imagination, kind of like Sam was referring
to before, thinking about the poetics of intelligence systems and the poetics of technology and
communications in a larger sense.
So I think a lot of that is really baked into much of what I do.
And it's just always propelled me to think of poetry not just in the conventional sense
of poems that you read off a piece of paper or that you read in the New Yorker or whatever,
but poems in a more expansive sense, poetry in a more experimental and conceptual understanding
of that term.
So when I say things like meta poetry, I'm really thinking of meta within the history
of poetry, the poetic tradition and thinking of it more in the sense of the Greek understanding
of meta as after, beyond, above, something that's kind of bigger and more all-encompassing.
And again, that kind of refers back to this notion of poetry as really being something
that is self-aware and something that helps us kind of understand ourselves and that activates
something.
It's not just storytelling, it's not just words on a page or words spoken into the air.
It's actually kind of a software program that when it's deployed is actually making something
happen.
It's very interested in kind of the mechanisms that surround the context by which these things
can happen.
And when I use terms like transhumanism or if I'm described as a transhuman poet, that
really I think has to do with the idea of transhumanism as a consideration of how advanced
technologies can really enhance the human condition.
And I mentioned before my first book and a lot of my practice is really about this.
It's about what it means to be human in an age that is really dominated by machines and
non-human intelligences in lots of ways.
And so within that context, I'm thinking a lot about poetry as a technology that has
enhanced our human experience and our human condition for more than thousands of years
and kind of creating a through line and thinking about how advancing and speculative technologies
like artificial intelligence, large language models like GPT-3 and soon GPT-4 and how things
like text to image tools can continue to expand and enhance our imagination and empower us
as human beings to understand ourselves in new ways.
So yeah, that's I think that probably is a pretty good summation of all that and also
explains why I'm really happy to be here in the web 3 space because a lot of these considerations
are very, I think are very fringe still in the world of poetry in the literary establishment
in the kind of more conventional writing communities.
The idea of something like bringing in an AI to co-author a piece of text is still anathema
in a lot of ways.
So I think it's been really important and really, you know, it's been very essential,
I think, to a lot of my practice to be able to explore some of these ideas and experiment
with these tools in the kind of very experimental and open-minded community that we have here
that's been, you know, fundamental, I think, to a lot of what I'm doing.
So I'm grateful for that.
Thanks, Asha, for that.
I love how you're all kind of linking together, you know, in your own way, AI, blockchain technology
and humanism, right?
I mean, it's all imbued in everything that each and every one of you have been describing
up to this point, which is pretty impressive.
I want to go to some general questions now for the panel, right?
And we'll start with you, Sam.
We have, we've been hearing and seeing a lot about open editions of late, right?
Almost drowning out one of one art.
Do you see this as a positive and something that's a sustainable trend or is it something
that we should be alarmed about?
Yeah.
There are some undeniable, beautiful upsides, right?
It's great to see many people enter into an artist's ecosystem affordably.
It's great to see artists make great payouts when the individual high-level 101 collectors
have either honed their taste to the point that they're kind of just after a few specific
artists or are just more price sensitive than they were back in the bull market.
And it's also just kind of a nice way to support artists.
These things are obvious, right?
There is the downsides that are just as obvious, flooding your own supply, these burn and redeem
games that may or not have exactly a follow-up plan.
But I don't really look at any of these new meadows rather with scorn or praise.
I do them as things to be studied.
You can either learn from them through participation or through studying.
And for this particular one, I've chosen to learn from observation mostly because I already
know where I'm going and it doesn't include this, right?
Lucy is an episodic story.
I've been working on it and it's arc for a long time.
The next piece in this arc is a couple weeks away.
The project after that is coming later this spring.
Doing that kind of puts me away from being reactive to whatever the game at the moment
is sometimes even at my own expense, right?
So to try to create work, I learned something in the creation process that usually demands
time out of me.
Time is something that I think about a lot.
The potential rewards for engaging in this particular wave, the risks of derailing design
that I put in motion for the next year, is just a little too high for me.
It feels like something that could maybe fill some coffers now, have under maybe the branding
or guys of accessibility.
But if I'm being very honest, it feels too disposable and interchangeable in this iteration.
There's something missing in it.
Creating work to be discarded for other work to be discarded.
Conceptually, this just honestly just does not align with my own value.
I don't fault anyone for participating in it.
That might be my own weakness, right?
Perhaps I hold art as too sacred because releasing this work with Lucy, it's changed my life
so drastically.
I hope every artist in this wave will take these drips and roll it into creating great
work, have a mess of new supporters that it dilutes nothing and it only opens each of
them to a bigger world.
But for my own goals, which are perhaps outside of that, I think time will agree with this
instinct.
In either direction, and maybe this is more important than anything, both in my desire
to skip it and what could be lost in that, and in others who participate in it, either
as an artist or as a collector.
Above all, I just think it's very important that everyone remember to take personal responsibility
for whatever may come.
Thanks, Sam.
Be thoughtful is what I pick up, right?
Be very thoughtful about what you do here.
You know, yeah, you know, over to you.
Same question.
I think that open edition can be great ways for artists to give an affordable access to
their work to anyone who'd like to own it.
I think people can experiment and play around because this industry is really young, so it's
good to play an experiment as long as the expectations are reasonable on both sides.
And it's art.
There's no road map there.
It's art and it's enough.
So it depends on why you do it.
It's important to be intentional.
Like Sam said, it's important to be thoughtful in both ways for either the artist and the
collectors.
And I haven't even done an edition yet.
I'm currently working on my first edition, so I don't picture open editions for myself,
but I can see why some artists do it.
I've bought some open editions because I really love the art and I've always wanted to own
one of the art from a specific artist.
But I've never sold an NFT, except from what I created any NFT that I bought.
I've never sold any ever yet.
So I'm not a flavor.
I'm not an investor.
An art lover, so my perspective comes from that stance.
Love that, love that, Ina.
Clear over to you.
Same question.
Yeah, sorry.
I had to find the unmute button there.
Yeah.
So this is a tough one.
Open editions are a scary thing, I think, for a lot of artists because of scarcity, right?
And worries that collectors will be hurt by doing that.
I thought about it a long time and I actually did an open edition myself.
But it was in a very specific context.
It was after I'd been getting a lot of comments that people were lamenting that they couldn't
collect a piece because my one of one floor went so out of range for most people and my
collections were also moving out of range.
Around the same time, NFT gateway reached out and offered to do a solo drop for an open
edition.
So I agreed, but what I did was I structured the drop to reward my collection holders and
my one of one holders.
And I also made it the shortest time window that you could with NFT gateway.
So that would be a 10 minute drop.
And I also sold a one of one sort of in conjunction.
So there was still a tier of that sort of game theory of scarcity involved.
So I think thoughtful is the good word for that.
I will say that open editions do build a broad community, which is always good.
And a broad community also means more opportunities for you as your audience grows and your reach
grows.
Theoretically more value to your scarce one of one work as well as long as you follow
an open edition with scarcity and as long as you don't do them repeatedly or for an
hour or a day or whatever long time window.
I think that there is a way to structure them so that it won't harm you and can be a good
thing, but you have to be very, very intentional about it.
Thanks, Claire.
So be thoughtful and use it as a leverage point for building community.
Great points.
Sasha, last but not least.
Yeah, so I actually really am interested in open editions as they kind of relate to the
history of literature and publishing.
I kind of mentioned before I am very intrigued in sort of thinking about blockchain within
the context of historical publishing innovations.
And open editions actually have a really important role in the history of literature in the
form of broadsides.
So when we were kind of moving away from handwritten literature during the advent of
printing press after Gutenberg's invention of movable type and all that, poetry broadsides
actually became a very important medium for cultural transmission.
Broad size in general, which are basically just kind of cheap readily, printable readily
available pieces of paper with text written on them, became a really essential way for
public announcements to be made and for poets to share their work and actually for songwriters
and lyricists to share ballads.
And there's just hundreds of years ago, so obviously quite different than what we're
talking about here, but I can't help thinking about open editions and editions in general
kind of in that context of the broadside.
And in fact, I've done quite a few projects that really invoke using blockchain as sort
of a bespoke printing press in homage to someone like Gutenberg in which we can create
many editions.
Sometimes they're all the same, sometimes they are algorithmically generated to be
slightly different, but this idea of being able to print something in multiple copies
and then share it with a broad audience I think is really instrumental in the history
of the dissemination of information and in turn the empowerment of the public and of
readers through that technological step forward.
So I think from that sense, I really like playing with the idea of what an open edition
represents.
I actually have an open edition right now with super chief Nifty Gateway, which is up
for another day or so, and I'm kind of interested in how it's being received and how people
are kind of engaging with it.
That's all very interesting to me.
And again, really like thinking about what it means to have a piece of work available
in that sense and at the same time have a whole roster of one of ones that do something
very different.
And I think one of the reasons I'm in this space is because I do see the potential for
web3 and for all the technologies that we're discussing to really help writers stand up
for the value of their work in a way that we haven't been able to before.
I think there is sort of an implicit understanding that writing, that literature, because it
can be easily reproduced and printed, that it's worth less than fine art, for example.
And one of the things that I'm very interested in personally and that I'm also working for
at the verse verse, which I mentioned earlier, is this idea that poems really have intrinsic
value and deserved to sort of be considered as inherently valuable alongside art in a
way that they haven't in the past.
And I think that that, in that sense, the role of one of ones is really critical.
Thinking about the ability of a poet to take a single poem and not just distributed as
a broadside or not just distributed within a printed collection of other poems, not just
distributed within a literary journal or within another magazine where that poem is packaged
together with hundreds of other pages of material.
But for that poem to be able to stand on its own, and especially for a poem like that to
stand on its own, liberated from between the covers of a book and stand as a one of one,
is also very, I think, sort of a new way of thinking about poetry.
So I see both the value for open editions.
I think, again, conceptually they're incredibly interesting and I think they can be very empowering
for poets as far as a way to actually make money from writing in a very novel approach.
But I also see the incredible value of one of ones for really kind of planting a flag
for the idea of poems as one of one artworks in their own right.
And again, that's something that I think is very different than the way poems have been
sort of treated in the course of human history.
Thanks, Ash.
I love the way you drew the analogy back to broadside, right?
I mean, effectively what was in many ways means and connecting with the people through
a means of communication and how you link that back to open editions.
That was pretty powerful.
Good stuff from the panel here.
All right, let's move on to our next question here.
This is an interesting one.
You hear, oftentimes, people describe the current art scene, whether it's digital art
photography, whether it's generative, as a little bit of a circle jerk or an echo chamber,
right?
And then what advice would you have for new artists and also collectors that are entering
the space, right?
What would be some effective approaches for them to engage in the community?
And how do we sort of expand and broaden the list of participants?
But Claire, I'll start with you on this one.
Yeah, sure.
So my advice for new artists and maybe collectors too, I hadn't thought about it as much.
But I would say lean into your art, obviously, but then when that starts to slow down, either
by your own kind of drive and inspiration kind of cycling or just by lack of engagement,
I would say lean into community building, Twitter spaces, education, that kind of thing.
So it's kind of like a pendulum.
You lean into the interior world and then you lean into engaging with others and helping
them where you can.
And then you lean back into your interior world and you just sort of repeat this pendulum
sort of motion.
And doing that, I think, replenishes your inspiration, but it also builds a following
of friends that are naturally interested in your work, naturally interested in wanting
to support you and be involved in the projects that you'd like to see succeed.
I think that, yeah, swinging sort of back and forth slowly has been very useful for me.
And that's what I would recommend.
Thanks, Claire.
Sam?
Yeah, I mean, look, it's an amazing time to be a digital artist right now.
Best time ever I've been doing this for a while.
Maybe it's a little bit harder because the tools are so accessible, sophisticated and
powerful, but I don't know.
I just think that's even better because it kind of puts a fire under your ass to pull
something real out of you.
As far as advice, man, I would definitely focus on the hard angle personally rather
than anything web-free specific because, I mean, you as an individual are a tiny little
spark, right?
You've got to nurture it with kindling care, knowledge and resources to make that sucker
grow.
Then you can attract the community to it, right?
You got to start close in to bring a little David White into the conversation.
Get your own house in order before worrying about others.
And for me, that is identify the areas that you struggle with the most.
Talking about being a painter here, that might be anatomy, color, light, or cocktail of any
of these.
Just any tension point where you find limiting the kinds of art that you are able to make,
in doing the hard work to learn what it takes to get what's in your head out on the canvas,
or whatever your medium is as fluidly as possible.
It just never shy away from things that you're bad at.
You can go infinitely into absolutely everything to find even one small thing to get good at
is a beautiful gift and you should feel no shame in struggling.
So long as you're putting time, energy, love, and humility into truly learning it, don't
mess around with pop culture too much.
Find out who you are, be in your mind and body in this world.
Best way to do that is to learn a lot of different things, as much as you possibly can, and to
start feeling your own gravity in one direction or another.
Because when you do feel that pull, and it can take a long time to get there, but when
you feel it, that's that time.
You've got to seize that and start going infinitely into building out that universe of that feeling
to go down every single little rabbit hole within it to see what does your mind look like when
you've extracted it out of you.
Don't dabble around and little one-offs here and there.
You're saying it doesn't matter how silly it is.
I paint monkeys, right?
But I really mean it, I really mean it when I make them.
I think just try to grow, stay with other artists, be vulnerable with them while being
hungry, share the struggles that you're having as an artist.
You're going to get a lot of vulnerability and return from others.
You mentioned circle jerk.
It's a great term for this because this is not about just being like two people being
sad artists together.
That's a nightmare.
You don't want to be in that little cycle.
You both have to have growth in mind.
These bonds that form from people helping each other push you.
It makes you learn together faster, better, more efficiently.
And in my view personally, most importantly, competitively.
Like that push and pull of different people learning at different paces trying to catch
each other.
It's like we're all just little wolves in the forest playing around with each other.
And it lights this fire in you, this soul to play the game.
Like two of my closest friends, a photographer named Jo-El and Victor Phoosius.
These are friendships that are not just for fun, right?
They're not just, oh, I like you.
How are you feeling?
How did you sleep?
We're here to push each other to help each other grow.
I love that.
So focus on the art and build the network and really challenge yourselves.
Nice one.
Over to you.
So I think that we have amazing tools to push the boundaries of visual storytelling in poetry
and whatever form of art that you want to share.
And the decentralized nature of this makes it accessible to everyone.
So I think that art is coming into this should experiment, try new things and not be scared
to fail.
And art has the power to transform your dreams into reality and reality into dreams.
So dream bigger and bigger.
Share your work, connect with people, make friends.
You will probably have people who will also hate your work.
Deal with that and really, I think that this is a great time to be an artist because there
is so much empowerment and there is so much things that you can do from your room.
You don't need to be in an art gallery.
You don't need to be chosen.
You have to choose yourself and you have to choose to put yourself out there and share
what the art that you created for the whole world.
There is a huge potential of connecting with people.
And so I think that the fact that there is kind of no limit is super exciting.
And it's a moment where more and more artists can share different types of works.
And we're open to it.
We're open to receiving it.
And we're in this together because it's such a young space that the technology and art
coming together.
And we're all experimenting at the same time.
So there's no bad ways because we are kind of learning on the way.
And for collectors, I think the same really by what you want, by what speaks to you, by
what means something to you and do research and connect with artists and create links.
The human links that we are making right now is something that is so, so, so important
and that I cherish every day.
Thanks, Ena.
So really zoom out, right?
I mean, as you said, we're super early and it's about the connections.
Love that.
Hey, Sasha, last but not least again.
Yeah, I'm loving all of this.
I guess two things that I would highlight that have been really important for me.
One is that I really think it's important, even though we're in this space that tends
to be so trend driven, I think it's really important to just really follow your own interests
and your own obsessions and go where they lead you.
I've been working with AI language since about 2018 in earnest.
And when I started doing it, nobody was using GPT to write real poetry or anything like that.
And I was definitely trying to take things into workshops and show my friends and got
a lot of very weird reactions.
And I kept doing it because it was really interesting to me.
I just thought it was fascinating and I was personally inspired and just exhilarated by
what I was discovering.
And lo and behold, fast forward a few years and now chat GPT is taken off and every time
I open a newspaper or listen to a podcast, people are talking about AI language and it's
just astonishing.
And I'm really grateful that I stuck to it and I didn't get discouraged in the beginning
by the fact that I was starting to share things and was sort of hearing crickets.
I think that it's very tempting, especially because the space is so quick and so fast
paced and can sometimes feel like a popularity contest.
It does feel like you want to do what seems to be successful.
And I would just say just remember that that's not necessarily going to work out well.
I think it's really important that artists go deep into their own fascinations and obsessions
and really just chase them wherever they can go.
And the other thing is that I think participating in the ecosystem is incredibly important.
When I first started minting, I took some time before my first mint to really get to
know some of the different ecosystems and the different platforms and to understand
what kinds of art was being minted where and to see where I felt at home.
And to really go where I felt like I had genuine relationships with people and I wasn't just
kind of dropping into something unprepared.
And I think over time what's really served me best has been actively and genuinely participating
in the ecosystems where I really feel that I belong and that I'm inspired by.
And that means not just dropping into mint and to show my work but to actively be involved
in the community to sort of look at what can be done to help build the community, to be
an active participant in collecting works by the artists that I admire, to help onboard
new people to the ecosystem, to actively kind of reach out and see if there's people who
are struggling and who want to be part of it.
All those things are really essential to the health of the overall ecosystem.
And ultimately will be beneficial to us all.
So I think that's really just kind of like a fundamental thing.
It's like table stakes to be part of this is that you really need to be engaged in a really
authentic and meaningful way.
So I think those are the two things that are sort of first and foremost in my mind these
days.
Thanks, Sasha.
Be authentic, engage, go deep, right?
And build a community and a network and expand from there.
Love it.
All right.
So we're going to move on to our final question.
And you know, Ina, I'm going to start with you on this one.
So if you could play Nostradamus for a moment and prognosticate, right?
Where do you see one of one digital art five years from now?
I think that there is no limit because art is the voice and expression of people.
And honestly, I think that it will just be considered art.
I'm not even sure that we're going to be using it as digital because in my shilling, many
people have been using digital art as to it's not like real art, but it is.
I think that it will the mediums where art are shared will change and will give access
to digital art into places where they don't exist for now.
And I'm very excited about this because this is a change.
It's a big change and change drives history.
And right now we're living through change so profound.
I feel like we're a moment where what we're doing right now will ship the culture.
And I'm super excited about it.
And art has always been used in the past to disrupt the status quo or support humanist
communities because revolution or evolution.
I can't wait to see where we will be in five years, but I think that we just started to
scratch the surface and it's going so fast that five years and our time is such a whole
world.
So I'm pretty excited to see where we'll be at.
Thanks, Ina.
Sasha.
Oh, goodness.
Well, I'm obviously thinking quite a lot about language.
And I think we're seeing things change almost on a daily basis when it comes to what's possible
with AI powered large language models.
So it's pretty wild even in the short time span.
So to think about where we might be in five years is mind boggling.
I do feel like when I take a step back, we are on the cusp of something more profound
and more pivotal than I think most of us realize.
When I think about the work that I'm doing with AI language, I tend to kind of consider
it in this larger frame of the history of human language from the development of the
oral tradition to the advent of written language.
And now it kind of feels like we're on the cusp of quite like on the right terminology
for it yet, but it's this new kind of generative literature that really embodies all the things
we've been talking about today, but literature and language that's powered by networked imagination
and collective consciousness and powered by community.
And I think that that is something that has so much potential to really shift not just
the way, for example, books are made and distributed or anything like that, but really to change
the way that humans think and how we share stories and how we understand ourselves and
our place in the world.
So I'm constantly trying to wrap my mind around it.
And related to that, I think that this is the reason I'm so excited about working particularly
with poetry and with language on the blockchain.
I think that the rise of poetry and FTS kind of nods to this larger shift towards this
new way of communicating and this new kind of understanding ourselves and the rise of
machine code as a new kind of universal language.
I think all of that is sort of that play when we're thinking about poetry and generative
text and the ability to preserve ideas via blockchain.
It's like all part and parcel of sort of the same general idea.
And I think more concretely, like in five years, I really think that we'll have seen
the rise of a poetry market, the rise of a new group of poetry collectors who are really
paying attention to poetry in ways that they haven't done before.
I think that we have this very established art market that's been in place for a long
time.
And I think as all of this new attention is kind of being shifted towards the role of
language in daily human life, not just in poetry, but in text to image generators and
using chat GPT and businesses and all this kind of stuff, I think that language is really
going to take on a very different role that cultural, you know, the cultural appreciation
of language will take on a different role.
So I think for that reason, no, it's going to be very exciting to watch the increase,
the influx of writers into the web three space.
And I think we're going to see a huge shift and a huge paradigm change there very soon.
Thank you, Sasha.
Clear.
Hey, yeah, so I will go ahead and warn you, I am quote unquote bullish on futuristic
predictions in general.
So this is probably going to be a little beyond what most people would envision, but I think
I'm probably right.
Five years.
So in the last year with AI specifically, we've come a universe, right, in terms of
space from where we were to where we are five years.
I see AI assisted creation of personalized metaverse worlds that that probably will be
the component that actually allows the metaverse to take hold like it should as a concept,
particularly using AR or VR, which is not developed enough yet.
But I know next year, Apple will be dropping some AR glasses that are lightweight and not
particularly ugly.
So I imagine we'll have more of a mass adoption moment there and VR will follow.
There is a creator named Cuddly salmon, which is a great Twitter handle who I love.
And she is using AI right now to create environments in virtual reality and project them live.
And so basically she puts on her headset and she's in the location that she just created
with staple diffusion.
I know there are also programs that now let you project AI images onto 3D environments.
So there's like a use case for texturing live, even theoretically, where you could type in
and texture live around you.
So anyway, that's sort of the zoomed in version.
The zoomed out version is I think that personalized independent media creation, exactly to your
taste from your bedroom is going to be the trend in five years.
And that will go for general NFT and art creation and with AI as well.
So art literature, films, video games, music, worlds, experiences, all by individuals or
by small groups working together with open source tools.
So I think we're going to see the death of some of these larger IP studios when that
happens, but in their place, I think we'll see the rise of creative collectives and independent
artists.
And that's going to be empowered by blockchain technology because it establishes provenance.
It sort of sorts out a lot of these scary, you know, financial and legal gray areas around
selling your work and establishing when it was made and how and all of that automatically.
So I would say start exploring the tools that are out there now and in five years, you'll
be very happy that you did.
Quite bullish.
Thank you, Clara.
Sam.
Damn, Clara, that was a hell of an answer and I agree with so much of that.
You know, I'm kind of in an interesting position, right?
There is this understandable, but maybe naive battle happening right now around AI art and
of what's authentic of what's human of what has sold.
For me, I'm on the other side of this, right?
My art is extractions.
Every single one of these things takes so much time and effort and crafted to make
them sing.
They're filled with detail, but the art in what I do is not found in perfect imagery.
It's found in the flawed attempt to create it.
And it's in that attempt where you will see my weaknesses, my fixation.
The areas where my mind has closed and my vision has narrowed.
So in my art is labor, like man hours poured into making singular images.
And because of these things, many, many that I speak to assume that I would be an enemy
of AI art, that I would either add to the moral panic of it or plant my feet in and
be scared that it will replace me.
But I am much more in the Claire School of Thought than that.
I am neither of these things because to me art is not about image making.
It is really about growth.
I see a multi-generational upheaval towards the creation of art at a massive magnitude.
AI is spreading this attempt of image making to everyone, all age ranges, socioeconomic
statuses, image making, and eventually art as we know it is about to become something
that every person in the world is capable of and in time will have access to writers
as Sasha suggested will become very powerful for a time.
Thinkers, scholars will become even more powerful as the line blurs further in our thoughts
alone serve as inputs for the generation of these world's self-generator worlds that
Claire suggested.
And I see this divide that may be existing right now, like do we preserve our individual
humanity or are we going to become part of a collective high mind?
It's neither, right?
They are dialectically coherent.
They overlap.
It's both.
It's just what we've talked about with one of one art.
You are able to document the source of yourself and your energy and you are also able to engage
in a broader community and world of art.
I view these things as very linked and I think that quite frankly, this conversation and
some of the people are in it are going to be leaders and trying to connect the philosophical
story and lore of humanity as an individual connecting to the larger unit without losing
yourself than just about any other artist I know in this space.
I'm very grateful to be up here with you.
And to be honest, I'm actually most curious about what Barack would say to this question.
If you're going to go Nostradamus, where do you see this?
Wow.
It's hard for me to follow big brains like y'all, right?
But I will say I'm very, very bullish.
I think what you've all shared, which is the human aspect of how we intersect across this
pyramid, if you will, the human aspect, the AI aspect, the art aspect, all coming together.
I think there's a perfect intersection of all of the disruption that will happen.
And I love the fact that it's putting power in the hands of the creator, right?
The creatives versus centralized organizations and big technology companies and studios,
right?
So, Claire's point on disrupting media, disrupting studios, disrupting big tech.
It's powerful.
It's the ultimate decentralization, open source movement and transformation so that anybody
back to a point that you made, Sam, that even little kids, right, are going to start being
very disruptive.
But I think what we're seeing with GPT-3 and with GPT-4 that's going to be out here shortly
is the absolute disruption and really foundational base set of language and prompt that's going
to allow for more complex primitives to be built or meadows as Sasha was saying, right?
So, I'm super excited.
I'm super thrilled.
And I just want to thank all of you for an amazing panel today and bullish on the next
five years.
I think we're going to continue to do really great things.
There's going to be a lot of noise as always, but I just want to thank each and every one
of you, Claire, Ina, Sasha and Sam, amazing session.
Thank you for joining and to all of the attendees, right?
A big, big, big, thank you for all of you who have stayed with us for the full hour and
have been a part of this and to UNIC for hosting us today.
Thanks, everybody.
Thank you so much.
This was really great.
Thank you for having me.
Thank you.