All right.
Hello everyone and welcome back for today's Metaverse Panel.
As you learn, it is hopefully people have found the right location.
We are not in quote unquote sector zero today.
We're on the very very beginnings of the Metaverse camp.
There's a big amphitheater and an outdoor park course that people jump around on.
We don't have classrooms or auditoriums or other things yet.
We do have a nice place to pick around.
Today we're joined with three important builders broadly, or I would call in the Metaverse ecosystem.
What we're going to do today is learn what they're doing, ask them easier or harder questions
as they know, and then find out what our future is going to look like.
As it's not just what's going to happen this year, I'd like to know what's going to happen
in 2035 so I can get mentally prepared for launching myself into the Metaverse.
The interesting here are the points of view of this week.
Then as always, at the end we will have some time for questions from the audience.
By all means keep track of what you'd like to ask and we'll cover it at the end.
Before we get into specifics, I think it is important that we give our guests the opportunity
to properly introduce themselves.
They are all three very interesting people.
The backgrounds and they are working on interesting projects.
We're going to go through one by one, learn a little bit about how they ended up here
working on these cutting edge topics and what specifically they're working on right now.
We'll do that and we'll get to the questions.
Let's start with the first.
Great to be here.
Thanks for having me.
A little on my background.
I'm Charlie.
I'm the founder of Restless and Charlie Cohen fashion brand.
I started the Charlie Cohen brand back in 2012.
Although it was a physical fashion brand, everything was very much based around internet
culture.
Throughout my fashion degree, which had been the prior four years, I was very involved
as a blogger and involved in a lot of digital discourse.
I was well aware by that time that my digital identity was as valuable, if not more valuable,
to me than my physical identity.
It was something that I really wanted to bring into physical collections.
Whether that was certain activations around each collection, what kind of platforms we
could build for having a conversation around the themes for each collection, plugging into
meme culture and so on.
Then after a couple of years, I'd say around 2015, we started getting to experiment with
AR and BR as well and being able to take this digital storytelling to another level and
really start creating alternative experiences to traditional fashion events like fashion
weeks, like typical lookbook shoots and so on.
It was a much more interesting way to connect with our community, who very much weren't
at these shows on the traditional fashion calendar.
2019, we started getting to work with the gaming industry.
That was really the first time I got deep into designing digital wearables and having
digital physical crossover.
Going into 2020, we were in a great position for the pandemic where we could create these
virtual immersive story worlds and retail experiences and digital collections as well.
Off the back of that, we ended up working with a lot of big brands like Pokemon, Hello Kitty,
Assassin's Creed, Reebok and started getting to do all of these proof of concept experiments
around digital and interoperability.
We weren't tackling interoperability from a blockchain perspective at that time.
We were just integrating with lots of different virtual social environments and game environments
where there'd be a version of an asset that was available in each of those spaces.
It helped to prove out the interest in interoperable identity, but it was still a pretty convoluted
experience.
As a user, you'd have to go into each of these individual environments, go through a separate
checkout flow, and then from a licensing side, everything would have to be contracted out
separately as well.
It was a nice idea, but certainly not scalable.
I went down the NFT rabbit hole as I was searching for some kind of tech solution to streamline
things, because the goal was to be able to have one central hub.
You could buy something once and then be able to take it into you as many places as you wanted.
As I got more and more involved in that space and that community, one, I realized that this
was a huge issue that everybody was talking about and trying to figure out.
Two, the ethos of Web3 and decentralization really resonated with me.
My own challenges about being involved in traditional fashion industry, traditional creative industry,
the ethical implications of that.
I really liked the idea of being able to be part of building something that could kickstart
a new generation of creatives and designers.
I shifted my focus from the brand and started building Restless at the beginning of 2021.
The main premise of Restless is it's an easy way for any creator or brand to easily build
and customize interoperable wearables that can plug into both open metaverse and traditional
game environments as well as have physical counterparts.
Excellent.
Matsu, do you want to tell us a little bit about your background?
Sure.
Thank you for having me.
I'm super happy to be here.
I'll tell you a little bit about myself and then it will just make sense what the company
that I'm building is.
I've been into VR now for something like the past seven years probably.
A little bit about myself, I grew up in the countryside of friends in the middle of nowhere.
I was the only teenager in my village.
So mostly I grew up with books and computers and they made most of my friends online.
When I was probably around 14 years old, the Oculus from Palmer Locky came out.
That was a very big deal back then.
My first thought was this is amazing.
If I could have this device, I could hang out with my own layer friends.
Problem is I was a teenager so I couldn't afford to buy a VR headset.
If you imagine it was like a thousand bucks at the time.
So I thought maybe I can build one by myself and I spend a more year building this VR headset
from scratch and basically ended up building the same thing as an Oculus but much cheaper.
I got super lucky.
There was at the time no resources on how to build a VR headset so I sort of had to figure
all of that by myself.
And in doing so I did things slightly differently.
And you might even say in some very specific aspects slightly better than Oculus.
So I did that at the time.
Facebook heard about it.
They flew me over to the US.
I got to spend time with the executive team.
Batman Binstow, their chief architect, loved their engineering team, loved the passionate
those people were about the VR.
But realized the leadership was in my opinion I felt like those people were coolest about
the VR and about where VR was headed.
And so I decided to take everything I'd built and open source it all.
The hardware, the firmware, the software, the algorithm, pretty much everything.
And dropped out of high school.
I was something like 15 years old at the time.
And dedicated the following four years, retrink to work on the edge of research in the VR.
Both from the hardware and software perspective and game engines and graphics and art.
And as many things we can talk about later.
And as a side note, if some of you are familiar with it back then I wrote one of the first
rendering plugin for Unity.
Which is used to make up half of the video games in the world.
And so I created some stuff that are still being used by people today in terms of like
the actual engine of how VR works.
So that was pretty nice.
And we have a fantastic relationship with Unity people in general.
And the turning point came, I'm sorry maybe I'm taking a little bit.
Here's a point to this story.
The turning point came.
That was the Quest 2, the VR headset that I'm sure you're all familiar with.
And that VR headset was, it was a before and after.
Everyone bought that VR headset.
They all played with it for about a week, right.
Trying to beat my score at bit saver or whatever that is.
And usually what you'll find is that after one week.
People just stop using it.
And they take it and they put it on a shelf behind them.
And just collecting dust and they just stop using it, right.
And the truth is the VR biggest use case is people are going to be using it for a week
and they're going to put it on a shelf.
And then maybe once or twice a year a friends visit or family visit and they're going to
be like, oh yeah, you want to try it out and you're going to take it out and have your
friends try it.
And that's pretty much it.
Okay, so that was VR back then.
To this day VR still has suffered from those problems.
And it turns out that I have very strong conviction as far as why there is the case.
And we can go very deep into that.
But I'm essentially convinced that as of right now the technology is already there to make
a VR headset that people use every day.
The designers are already there.
They're storytelling the marketing, all of those things could be made.
I just think that meta is not the right company to do it.
And so I went out there, explained exactly how to do it to other companies.
You know, for instance, Unity, right.
I love to make people from Unity.
I went to them and explained to them, hey, this is how you make VR so that it does not
make people sick anymore.
And Unity said, that sounds awesome, go and ask someone else to build it.
I was like, okay, sure.
So then I go and ask NVIDIA because they use some of my stuff as well.
And NVIDIA says, that sounds awesome.
Go and ask Qualcomm.
So I go and talk to Qualcomm and you just did basically no one wanted to build it.
And so at the time I reached out to a novel, a revicant, which might be familiar with
is an investor in crypto and metaverse and many stuff.
And novel convinced me to build my own company.
And so I just started this company and said, if no one wants to build it, I'm going to
build it myself.
And we started off really focused on software, then started expanding into the hardware part
of it.
And now we're starting to go deep into the design and marketing of that whole thing.
Nothing that we've done is public yet, but I'm super happy to talk about it.
So we've been very stealthy.
And just so you have an understanding of where the company is at.
So we were based in Mountain View, California.
We've raised quite some money.
We're actually the best funded company in VR hardware currently.
And we're a super nice team that I'm very proud of, people from Apple, people from Sony
and people from metal.
And some of those people that worked on stuff that you've seen before, some of those people
you've even seen on stage before, as those people were on stage during Apple's keynotes.
And so yeah, that's what we do today.
That's what I work on.
And I guess as a tiny bit more piece of a context, I come very much from hardware, but
sort of then graduated into trying to become much better at software.
And the past, I would say here, also, has been really about design and marketing.
And so I guess where my perspective might be interesting for a question is, I have a pretty
good understanding of what it takes for VR to go mainstream, but also the history of
host of goes mainstream.
And it might be interesting to talk about some of my perspective on why is it that some
things like crypto or VR might seem like they are experiencing what some people might call
the winter.
And how do you get through that?
And maybe I can bring some historical perspective on that.
So that's me in a nutshell.
Fantastic.
And Brian, you're talking about yourself and on the shoulder.
After this introduction is pretty hard for me to be able to tell myself.
Yeah, I mean, the story of On-Samper and myself is really the story of a kid who wanted to
do something useful in VR3.
I think I started getting interested in 2krypto when I was about 12 or 13.
A long time ago.
And I didn't directly get into crypto, but got into really admired the tech.
Took me about 10 years to finally get him and build a product in it.
In the meantime, I was building product and I left a program and such.
My dad is in the art world.
So I had been around art creation and art and contacts with artists, et cetera, for my
whole life.
When mid 2020, I find out about NFTs and directly it clicks.
I directly noticed what it can do for creatives, what it can do for the relations that creatives
have with their collectors.
Where in the art world, there's a very central assistant for people to go and get the approval
of dealers and galleries and whatnot.
I thought Web3 and NFTs could come into free up creatives all around the world.
Any kid like myself from Morocco and I know so many examples would be able to go and sell
stuff on foundation and whatnot and make money without ever having to kiss the hand
of a random art dealer in Morocco.
So I thought that was pretty interesting.
But at the time when I started to look at this, there were very few platforms that would
allow people to story tell with art.
I think at the time the biggest platforms were Decentraland and CryptoVoxels in the immersive
space and then the other options for curation would be in 2D.
Of course, adding a dimension makes it easier for people to curate art and to enjoy art.
So we needed a proper immersive experience or immersive experience platform for people
to showcase and discover art and to visualize Web3, the culture in Web3 in a sense.
But there were none and the only way to get into curation in Web3 at the time was to go
buy a lamp on Decentraland and hire an architect and do a bunch of very redundant actions just
to be able to exhibit art.
Most people were actually going and buying a lamp on these platforms to do exactly those
functions.
And so I went and thought, hey, there is definitely a use case somewhere here where people want
to showcase their assets in immersive spaces and connect around immersive spaces.
I do not know what this metaverse is ever going to be.
I do not know what exactly people are going to want to do, but I know I can have a link
with a bunch of people right now that are early adopters that want to experience with
these technologies.
And so the idea was we're going to go and build this simplest product for people to
place and discover assets in immersive spaces.
And from there, try to listen as much as possible for the community's feedback and what people
want to do in these immersive spaces to just build layer after layer after layer for something
that makes sense.
What we're doing today.
And in OM, for example, like I would have never guessed when I was in this very same
bedroom at my parents house in Morocco when I started the company two years ago.
But again, I think the one thing that we've had within the team is that we've always been
very open as to what this could be, what the metaverse landscape is going to be, what
the immersive web should be.
And we just kept on listening to our community, building another layer and building another
functionality.
So I think the story of a one-siber as a company that's fully bottomed up, that listens to
people, that will always go in and find the latest piece of feedback that our users want
and will go in and implement that so that we end up having a product that truly resonates
with real humans rather than just having ideas about what an immersive world should be and
just developing it from the ground up until it's ready.
So yeah, that's pretty much me and my story.
Okay, this was fantastic.
And I'll have about 11 million questions.
Let me start with some specific questions addressed to specific people.
And then later we'll do the more integrative ones.
And again, I want to start with Charlie.
I want to give you the opportunity to address the following thing that I have heard one
billion times.
I don't want digital wearables.
Why do I need digital wearables?
I want real clothes.
I want a real purse.
Why would I spend money on that stuff?
Obviously, this is not NFT people.
Let's call it normal people.
Right?
So when I've had this discussion, what are NFTs good for?
Not saying different things, but one of the things I always say is digital wearables.
And like 80% of the time, this is the answer.
Can I give my response with my guesses?
You probably have a better, more nuanced thought than this.
So the floor is yours.
Sure.
So I think usually my first question in response to that mentality is, have you ever used a
profile picture?
Have you ever curated an Instagram feed?
Have you ever used a filter on social media?
Generally the answer to at least one of those things, if not all three of them, is yes.
And then we can start digging into, well, clearly you care about your digital identity
to some extent.
And as technology develops and your digital identity is represented increasingly in 3D
spaces and as an avatar, then wearables are going to be the equivalent to changing your
profile picture or curating your Instagram feed.
And then also is always nice to point out the $60 billion skins industry within traditional
gaming as well.
There is a complete precedent for a whole generation, two generations, the value that
digital identity enough to be investing heavily in game wearables.
And this doesn't even have the functionality of NFTs where you own it, where you can take
it into other spaces, where it's, you know, often you can't resell it for actual money.
And NFT wearables are taking something that is already a massive industry and making it
even more valuable and even more scalable.
But I think usually the key is just like focusing in on digital identity, which is something
that most people have been participating in for the last couple of decades.
And then it starts to click a little bit more why sometime in the future they might
be investing in that in a slightly different way.
Okay.
So I agree with everything you said, obviously.
Now what if someone says that's fine.
Of course I have a profile picture on Instagram or LinkedIn or Twitter and they might even
be different.
But I didn't spend money on it and I put one once to like I'm changing it all the time.
Is this something in gaming, I hear you on gaming, but that's like I don't know if people
will play a lot of games.
Is this just something for people with games?
I'm a normal person.
I have a social media presence.
I'm not a big gamer.
Is this just something that's not for me or is it going to be different?
Well, I guess then it comes to the concept of fashion and subculture and community full
stops.
It's like, have you ever done anything within the physical world, made a physical purchase
because in some way it connected you more to a community.
In some way it was a flex.
Have you ever bought a pair of limited edition sneakers?
What was the reason behind that?
And then it's sort of taking that and like, okay, well, if the only place or the primary
place that you're going to be connecting with that community or showcasing that flex is
in digital, then isn't the digital version of that asset actually more valuable?
I think the first thing, why are you buying some combination of why you buy a limited edition
sneaker and what your profile pictures and why it changes and the skins somewhere in
there is the reality.
I think there is probably some room for us as a community to find a shorter, piffier way
to get this across.
I don't know why the team Bitcoin figured this out right now to talk about Bitcoin.
You're holding it, digital gold or what have you.
There's probably something there because it's a very common response on this topic.
Practically it'll probably just happen naturally.
Maybe we can accelerate.
Anything you want to add there, should I go to McSee?
I think we can go over to my team.
Hi, McSee.
Let me make sure I understood this correctly.
You went around to all the biggest technology companies in the world all like multiple tens
or hundreds of billions of dollars or trillions and you have concluded none of them know how
to build a concept so you're going to build your own.
Did I understand this correctly?
You can say that way.
I'm summarizing it the way I understood it.
You were going to build a better headset.
This is the takeaway.
I think we at the company, it's not many people.
I think we have a shot at building a better headset.
I mean that's in the very holistic sense.
I think one critical aspect of, as I'm sure you realize actually being in crypto, is it's
certainly about the product, it's also about the messaging of the product and your ability
to convey that and to educate people about it.
And yeah, I'm happy to be more specific but I think the way you broke it down is it would
be accurate, although we don't say it like that.
Right, of course not because you're modest and appropriate.
What does a better headset mean?
Facebook has put, I don't know how many billions of dollars into a headset.
Okay, well that's cool.
I'm a smart guy.
Mine's going to be better.
Why is it going to be better?
How is it going to be better?
What's missing today that when your headset comes out, will be much happier?
Sure.
I think that's a fascinating question and one way I'll try to answer is rather than going
into the very specific difference between my headset and their headset, maybe what I
can try doing and if it's interesting, we can keep pulling on that thread, is talk a
little bit about the cultural differences between the people making decisions at the
Metap or Apple and the people that I'm a part of and that most people in this sort of metaverse
movement are part of and where are the cultural differences between them.
And the reason for that is one of my belief is, you know, if you look at a company like
Google, Google has tried many times to compete with Apple in the smartphone market and Google
has infinite amount of money and yet they're not able to compete with Apple, right?
Like their phone are setting much less units than the iPhone.
So they're not able to compete with the iPhone despite having infinite amount of money.
So it means that there's something else that Apple has that Google does not have and that
thing is a set of belief and that thing is essentially culture.
And so rather than telling you exactly the specs in terms of difference, I think it's
worth it to talk about the cultural differences between Metap or Apple and those companies
and us.
And if I try to break down the cultural difference, the most important point and I think that
if you have one thing to take away from me, it would be that it's the fact that to those
people, virtual worlds have a zero sum game relationship with the real world.
So it essentially means is that to those people, the time you spend in a virtual world is time
lost in real life.
It's like minus one hour spent in that virtual world.
It's like one hour that you're not spending in real life and it's like this idea of like
wasted time.
And I think it's pretty deep into the psyche of those people.
And so one of the consequences of that is in the way they designed the headset and the
way they designed the experiences and the marketing of it, basically what they try to
convince you of is take your life and move your entire life to the metaverse.
And then the reaction that people have to that is, well, this is going to take away
stuff from my real life that I would rather not do in VR, right?
The predict perception of VR is pretty dystopian because people think that, no, I want to make
friends in real life, not only in VR.
And so the mental framework of those people is always trying to put in opposition the
real life in VR.
Whereas what I find with my friends and myself, instead of the people either from my generation
or with the same kind of interest is that they really think of virtual worlds in their
daily life as sort of this balanced relationship where some of the most valuable time in their
real life came as a result of the time they spent in virtual worlds.
And so in that sense, I would say the core difference is meta is trying to think about
how to keep you inside the VR headset as long as possible.
I'm trying hard to think about how can I make you very happy when you take the VR headset
off?
It's like, what do you get away from the experience?
And so I realized it's a little bit abstract, so let me make that, let me get into more specific
examples.
Let me try to think of a great one.
All right.
I'm sure most of you are familiar with the art chat.
And I'm sure as many of you are familiar with Facebook Horizon, which is the competitor
to the art chat.
And it seems as though regardless of how much money meta is pouring into Horizon, Horizon
is not able to compete with VR chats.
VR chat is just swinging whereas Horizon is not.
And if you try to think, how is that possible?
Why can't they just copy VR chat into the exact same thing?
The reason why that is not possible is that as much as the people using VR chat every
day and I've used VR chat a lot, love the time they spent inside VR chat, the most valuable
thing they get out of VR chat actually happens outside of VR.
It's the fact that those friends that you've made in VR chat, they just become friends
as a whole in your daily life, the rest of your life.
And you might even try to meet them in real life.
It's the ability to be able to go inside VR chat.
And after you've had maybe a long or stressful day, took to people and sort of have them
and have like those sort of deep emotional meaningful conversation, and then you get
out of VR and you feel better.
It's like all those things that happen in VR and directly reflect back to your real
life.
And somehow every time something has that characteristic, it happens in VR but reflects
in real life, meta is just not able to do it right.
And instead what they offer you is, instead we're going to take, we're just going to
increase the amount of time you can spend in VR.
So if you look at the feature list of Horizon, they prioritize stuff like bring your laptop
to Horizon.
Because that's the way to sort of day thing that's going to like try to keep you longer
in Horizon as opposed to how do we increase the ratio of meaningful conversation in Horizon
as opposed to non meaningful conversation.
And like the way you design that changes, like the way you think about it changes widely
the design of like this from that form.
So that would be like my very, very high strike high level answer that like I'm happy to dive
into it, but I'm also realizing you might want something a little more specific.
So I also share some specific details about my headset in terms of the philosophy of the
headset itself.
Yeah, I'm trying to be mindful of the time at the same time, but I also want to give
you a little bit of a nuggets about the headset.
So I'll choose one vertical and then I'm happy to talk about one.
One vertical would be how do we think about comfort?
And for that, I have to tell you a little bit more about again, how does company design
their VR headset?
The way VR headset is usually designed is you have a team that's going to come up with
a list of features.
Some of them are going to be hard requirements.
Some of them are not stuff like facial tracking or body tracking or whatever.
Once you have those features, you define what you need to achieve those features and then
you build those gigantic prototypes like the one you saw in maybe Zercoverer's video.
And once you have the gigantic prototypes, you try to make them smaller and then you send
that to a factory, try to make it as small as possible without it breaking and then you
have a headset and then you put that to market.
That's how VR headsets is traditionally designed.
One of the things we've decided to do at UNIGAT is to absolutely refuse to do that.
And we start the other way.
We try to make VR headsets just made out of plastic and we just try to make them as comfortable
as possible.
And then we put them on a ton of people, we put weights inside and we try to see when
they stop being comfortable.
And we find those threshold and we spend a lot of time trying to find what is comfortable
or what is not and then we work it backwards and we say, okay, what features can we fit
inside the headset without it being stopping to be comfortable.
And what we find is that there's a lot of features out there that you might not have
in the UNIVR headset.
But that's because we started from this perspective of comfortable, maybe I had to remove a few
features and our criteria when we looked at that feature is does that feature and that's
how it ties back to the beginning of my story, does that feature benefits you once you take
off the headset, yes or no.
And does it make a significant difference?
So for instance, a VR headset that you might have heard of, the PyMax, it's like this one
kilogram gigantic thing that I'm not making this up is like this large.
And the PyMax, I don't know if I can say this publicly, but the difference in resolution
between our headset and the PyMax, which is the headset with the highest resolution of
all time, it's like, again, this one kilogram gigantic big thing on your face.
The percentage of like more resolution that they have is in the single digit branch.
That's like, well, I'll share for now.
But for that single digit, it's so hard to increase resolution that it results in this
like gigantic system that is incredibly heavy with like two big cables plugged at the back
of it.
And that system is indeed like, I don't know, like four times higher resolution than a
Quest.
But the price of it is like being so huge.
In our case, we're not quite to that resolution, but we've been so hot core about ergonomics
that like it fits into something that is about a tenth of the weight of that thing.
So this is probably one of the most ergonomic VR headset out there.
And again, that's because we ask ourselves at the end of the day, if the resolution was
like even twice as much when you take off the headset, what are the chances that you're
like, oh, yeah, like this is really making my day much better that the resolution was
like twice as much.
It matters, but not as much as people think.
And thus it shouldn't be, it shouldn't have that big of an influence on the design.
So anyway, there's a long answer, but that's sort of how we approach things.
Long answer and still did not reveal any trade secrets.
We did not manage to, you know, yeah, I'll find out.
All right, let's go to Ryan.
I don't know if Ryan's on the very specific.
Yes, it started art focus now it's doing many things, but for me, what it always attracted
me to on cyber and I've spent an infinity amount of time working on on cyber is grand
of those is your role objective of it being open and built on open standards.
What does that mean?
What does open mean?
What does close mean?
How does it different what are the opportunities challenges, et cetera?
Yeah, I mean, like, so one thing is we on on cyber is a child of the work through space.
So, so like we started because we wanted to like fulfill the need within the work space,
not necessarily because we wanted to build general immersive experiences or whatnot.
So the whole point has been that we have been building with very strong foundations for
a progressive decentralization.
I think there's a lot of companies in this space that like are built within with different
principles and want to be open.
But at some point, like when your foundations are aren't able to be open, like it's very
hard for you to ever be part of a lot of space.
What that means in our case is that from the ground up, we built on cyber on free opens
or software.
So there's no proprietary engine involved and we've never we're never going to have to
answer to a big corporation that would own the proprietary engine or have a say in what's
happening with their engine, which is not the case for everyone.
And it's it's hard to do because like you have to rebuild a lot of things from the ground
up.
But I think it's the way that you can truly be free long term and have your users and
community free.
Number two is that we make sure that all assets are stored in the open.
So there's like the whole principle of Web3 is your content and you can take it whatever
you want.
There is nothing within on Saber that isn't stored in the open.
Of course, like there's different storage is not necessarily always the most efficient
or faster performance type of solution for first storage, which is why we have always
have like surfacing CDNs and different services that do things faster.
But at the end of the day, all data is stored in the open and can be taken and taken from
like, let's take the example of all spaces built with on Saber or this space metacampus
that we're on right now.
It is yes, stored on CDN, but also stored on IPFS.
And if need be if ever tomorrow something happened and on Saber wasn't working anymore,
you could totally take this space taken to another platform that uses the same standard
we do, which is a pretty common standard in the web called GLTF, which is like what I
would say is the equivalent of an HTML in the immersive web.
And you would be able to run exactly the same space, exactly the same architecture and completely
different platform.
So for me, what open means is number one, you can restrict access to it and everyone can
participate, which is why we don't have Google login or anything similar.
But you can just log in with any type of wallet and soon enough can log in without a wallet
even.
Number two, I think that I spoke about it before, you cannot have a proprietary tech
at the basis of the tech.
And so we have chosen not to go with anything proprietary or a proprietary engine.
And that there is very low, low cost to switching.
So you don't want to make it so that people come in and are locked into it.
Like most web two platforms do, like Instagram does or whatnot, like there's no way to go
port your content easily.
But with us, the idea is to have all those principles and follow them very, very closely.
Of course, we don't know what, like, as I said, On Saber is a work in progress.
It's a bottom up type of product.
And we cannot know everything we need to do to do to everything we need to decentralize
in order to be truly open from the ground up.
But all our foundations are very open.
And as we go without losing too much time on, oh, I think this should be decentralized
or stored on chain or off chain or whatnot, we can go pretty fast while having a clear
avenue for decentralization whenever we know exactly what that means and how that can be
done efficiently.
So yeah, that's pretty much like what I think we are doing right now to be able to be part
of the open metaverse.
Yeah.
Okay.
Usually, I mean, this is the story of many things.
Usually centralized solutions at a minimum start with some advantages, right?
They usually tend to, you know, they're more convenient or they're more easily packaged
up or they come with more prepackaged features or what have you.
And sometimes it has worked out that open standards have taken a hold of HTML, not the
information superhighway.
Other times, you know, Linux for the desktop never really happened, but Linux eventually
over decades when the server market.
How do you view the strategic landscape here between a wide variety of closed or semi-closed
platforms, you know, using quite mature game engines in most cases, right?
You know, Unreal Engine or Unity who don't have to worry about any types of don't have
to spend any cycles, development cycles or feature cycles and performance cycles trying
to keep it decentralized and so on.
Whatever it is going to deliver.
We're going to deliver end user experience.
How do you see this?
It's a very interesting question.
And I think we have to go back to our text text to try to start answering this question.
Whenever we, when I started on Saber, there were, of course, like many choices we had
to make.
Like, what do we want to, what's the target for the build on Saber?
What, how people are going to access it?
Like, what's going to happen there?
We chose the browser because to me, today is the most open type of distribution channel
to go and reach people with apps.
Like, web apps are very hard to be censored and can be distributed as you want if people
have a link.
So we decided to go with that.
And with that, chose 3.js as a technology for like the basis of our tech.
So the Linux in this case would be 3.js slash web.gls slash web.gpu, I guess.
And then our focus is to make sure that we can build the best possible experience for
our users and build the best possible UX for people to come in and enjoy being in those
immersive worlds, which are themselves like run by web.gls, web.gpu soon and free open
source software.
Okay.
Let's do another round on kind of state of today in adoption.
I'm going to go back to Charlie.
How many, where are digital wearables now?
Right?
Where are people using them?
How many are the using them?
What types of things are you seeing developing in the background that, you know, our average
person today might not know about?
And how do you expect this to change over the next one, two, three years?
Sure.
So I think like the key use cases for digital wearables right now are either in-game and
like thinking more traditional gaming industry, whether it's like the daily active user base,
generally a younger audience as collectibles.
So I guess you're more like typical web three speculative NFT investment.
Or as a way to unlock either physical redeemables, so like physical wearable utility, or more
as like ticketing to events.
So a lot of traditional fashion brands that have tried to enter the NFT space have based
the utility around like access to fashion shows, like, yeah, special, like VIP access
within their flagship stores and so on.
So everything is quite heavily focused around existing fashion use cases, like you're, you
know, you're literally wearing it in the physical world in a game, or it's giving you some kind
of status.
And I think right now, like the best web three use case for digital identity is the PFP.
And you know, you wouldn't necessarily think of that as fashion, but it's doing very much
the same thing.
It's like signaling you as part of a community.
It's saying something about your status.
It's saying something about how early you are into the web three space.
You know, it's communicating a lot in the same way that the passion does.
So I see the evolution of wearables, like what does the PFP mean as we start to socialize
more in 3D spaces as interoperable identity in open metaverse actually becomes something
that there is like clear use case for.
So, you know, it relies a lot, I think initially on a move from like text based social media
like Twitter and Discord into social media happening within 3D spaces, which, you know,
there are lots of amazing builders very proactively working on at the moment.
The like the gaming use case isn't going to go away, but we are, you know, away off traditional
game developers allowing external assets into their games.
There's definitely an intent from like big game developers like Epic Ubisoft roadblocks
to start, you know, exploring how they integrate with web three.
Nobody really wants to be a first mover.
There's a lot of pushback from the gaming community as well.
So I guess one of the first things that needs to happen there is like just entirely abstracting
away from talking about web three and NFTs and just, you know, creating new language
around it.
There's visceral reaction from their existing player bases.
I think one of the first things that we'll see around interoperability within game developers
is just within properties that that developer owns.
So like for example, Epic opening up wearables and assets.
So it could be used across like full guys, Rocket League Fortnite and so on.
And I think we will start to see specific partnerships with these game developers where
they are exploring a level of interoperability, but it's still going to be extremely pleased
and sort of, you know, very narrow in terms of the partners that they work with.
In terms of traditional fashion industry coming in, I think it's a less interesting proposition
than new gen brands that are web three native starting up.
I think there's a, as we kind of touched on with the first question you asked me, there's
a whole lot of convincing for a, you know, a large subset of people of the value of digital
wearables.
I think the luxury fashion brands that came into the space over the last couple of years
and by consulting for some of them were extremely surprised to find that none of their existing
customer base were interested in adopting a web theory or buying NFTs and that actually
their entire web three business needed to be contingent on their involvement in the web
three community.
So there's still like a huge division, I think, between like Jen Alpha, Gen Z who are used
to the idea of digital wearable utility, a more traditional, I guess, as he said, like
normal demographic where you need some kind of physical utility to make it make sense
and web three audience where there's the understanding, like collecting something and having value
over time.
But I think, yeah, the main, the main first big step for adoption is social media in 3D
spaces being the norm.
So this is fascinating what you said because I think it matches what we see for the most
part in art.
So the major NFT art collectors are not on the whole, there's some famous exceptions,
but like on the whole, they are not big traditional art collectors.
They are people who grew up in the web three space and then found that NFT art varies types,
represents their values and culture and what have you.
You're saying the same thing is happening in fashion?
Yes, exactly.
You have very divided demographics and it's, you know, it's completely based on how do
you value your identity and if your identity is born of internet culture, like most of
us in this space, that's where you're going to pin more value is where you're going to
be willing to spend more time, more money, like whatever investment looks like to you.
Whereas if status or identity has always been rooted in your physical world or physical
community, it's yet very difficult to imagine that switch.
And so my parents and family are in the traditional art space, like art dealers and tea dealers.
So I've seen like that side of what status looks like and the challenge in explaining
the value of what a digital collectible looks like to somebody who's in Thai business is
dealing in physical, and I can see like Ryan is smiling.
Same situation.
I mean, I say that my mum was signed up to this university course and it's like fully
degenerated into web theory, but certainly it's like a big learning curve.
Whereas I'd say especially my younger friends and also younger team members, absolutely
normal to them that they would be spending more time worrying about what their digital
identity, digital community and online friends are up to you.
This is fascinating.
I think it's right.
I think we're going to have a generational shift.
It'll be massive, but it'll take time because it's generational.
Where do you think the, I mean, nobody knows for sure.
And there's of course huge examples on the other side, right?
There's some more digital native older people.
There's some boomerish younger people.
We know that's the case, but broadly, if you had to like pick a number, what age or what
year of birth or where does the internet native generation start?
Who are they?
I would say it's Jen Alpha, internet native in terms of that, like it's just the standard
for them that all of their socializing takes place in like avatar based virtual environments.
They already understand the idea of trading in digital identity.
Like it's the eight to 12 year olds right now who are already doing that in roadblocks
and Minecraft.
I think with Gen Z and this is just like speculative based on like my guess my own observations.
I think there is a little bit more seriousness in that generation where the idea of, I guess,
like, you know, exploring identity, like starting a business, trading within the digital world,
like those feel, I guess, not as comfortable compared to like the younger like siblings
and cousins in my family who are this like younger roadblocks generation.
So you know, we pin like so much hope on Gen Z is like, okay, this is going to be the
metaverse future.
But I think there's actually a lot more resistance there.
And if you spend any time on TikTok and have ever looked at posts around NFTs, the like
the vitriol from that generation around NFTs and Web3 is probably the highest of any generation.
So Gen Z is going to let us down again.
I mean, sorry Gen Z.
Very interesting.
All right.
Let's switch to let's see.
Let's see.
You said something in your initial remarks and I laughed because I went back in 2013.
I think it was 2013.
It was Christmas of 2013.
It was in New York and the first Samsung gear VR device came out.
It wasn't 13, it was 12.
So I bought it.
I have this general who I'm for sure the oldest person in this panel.
But I have a general and I will share it with everyone.
It's a good way to try and not become outdated.
Anytime a new technological thing happens, I just do it without thinking about if it makes
sense or not.
Because if you think about if it makes sense, as you pass, I don't know, the age of 25 or
30 somewhere in there, you suddenly think like nothing actually makes sense.
Oh no, that's not the things that, who wrote it, Douglas Adams wrote it.
Things that happened before you were 25 are natural state of the world, right?
Things that when you're 25 to 40 are an exciting career opportunity and things that are invented
after 40 are terrible and against the natural order of things, right?
This is how you will, this is how humans default work and you should assume you'll be a default
human.
And so you should assume your bias is going to be against new things once you get passed
on in 25 or 27 or 30.
So I have this general who now, once I started in a very American, whatever, whatever happens,
anything new, I just do it.
I take away from myself the decision of should I spend money on a VR set?
There's a VR set I'm gonna buy it.
And then I do my Virgo.
I put it on.
I hang it at like that helicopter and Iceland scene or something.
I was like, holy, I'm not gonna say this was a university course, but this is the most
incredible thing I've ever seen.
This is like, so I called my mom and my dad and everyone I know and I was like, you gotta
come over and everyone's like, you gotta be kidding me.
This is amazing, huh?
And a month later, I was sitting on the shelf gathering desk.
And I have the Oculus channel and it's more or less sitting on the shelf and I've gone
in to see all of it right like that.
But here I am actively building a platform that displays on the web and displays in VR.
And I would say 99% of the time I spend in that platform is on the web.
It's not in VR.
It's quite frankly, at least for me, I find it to be kind of a pain.
Yes, I want to check out something at home going through the browser is easy.
Going and finding their headset, putting it on, messing up my hair.
Oh, I forgot to charge it.
Oh, I had to plug it in all this stuff.
God forbid because someone comes sees you.
You look like a complete weirdo, right?
Like if someone comes in and likes it.
So what's going on there?
Like when are we actually going to adopt VR?
What needs to happen for us to adopt VR?
Does it matter if we adopt VR?
I assume it does given you're spending your life building VR headsets.
Tell us about this topic.
Sure.
That's a fantastic question.
I love it.
Let me give you the super short answer first.
The super short answer is interesting because it builds on what I used set before 6.5.2.9
in Charlie, which is if you look at the very, very young kids like I look at my cousins,
they are already using VR almost every day.
So you already have, in fact, millions of kids, the very, very young ones that are using VR,
that there is almost the only one using it very actively.
But still that does not answer your question of why do, like, why is it depending on the
process?
And I think you're right.
It absolutely is.
Some of you might have seen that Fred going on on Twitter.
It's a fascinating one.
It's like someone that basically explains that it took them about 35 minutes to get into
a multiplayer session with their brother in VR.
And so you describe the process pretty well.
Usually the way it goes is you grab the headset, you try turning it on.
Nothing happens.
You turn it down, press the button again.
Okay, because when it's turned off, you have to press for a little longer, actually.
Then it turns on and actually, no, there's no battery left.
So you have to charge it because the battery drains with sub plug.
So you charge it for about, as you end up, it's like two hours and a half.
You charge it for a while, then you take it, then you turn it on.
Then you have to, for some reason, sometimes you have to pair it again with your phone.
Not even really know why.
Turn on Bluetooth, 30 seconds.
That's like a, actually I shouldn't say that to you.
Actually, no hope when it happens.
The number is crazy.
It was a bug they tracked back at the middle.
And it's a crazy one.
Anyway, you pair it again.
Okay, it's spared.
Now you have to update your Facebook account or Oculus account.
Actually, if you have an Oculus account, because like you were from the early days, you have
to turn your close accounts to a Facebook account.
Then you get an AR message that does not work on mobile.
You have to go on your laptop, try to log in again, and then it tells you you have to
turn your Facebook account into a metal account.
I'm really, like I swear, I'm not making this up.
So you've converted to a metal account, you log in again from the headset, which by the
way, it's going to be the worst experience in your life if you use a password manager.
Because most likely you're going to be taking the headset and be like, everything on your
laptop like that, and with the controller trying to type the text.
Okay, you've gone through all of that, congrats.
Now you have to update the software on the headset.
So it's going to turn off and update and everything.
And then once you do that, you realize actually on the Quest, or some reason, the apps of the
OS and the OS itself are not like updated together.
So now you think, oh, I'm good.
I'm just going to log in with my friends.
And you click like the friend app, which is like the most basic operating system app you
could imagine.
Oh, no, that one needs to be updated separately.
You're going to update that one.
And then you're going to try to join with your friends and you're going to struggle so
hard to join with your friends.
Like I don't want to even describe that process to you because like then I'm just going to
like hijack the whole course.
Just talk about that.
And finally, when you're supposed to be in with your friend, you're all right.
That's it.
Like you can hear each other.
For some reason, just like a regular call, but at least you can hear each other.
So now maybe you're going to start, let's say one of my favorite game, show up to the
developers, Dimeo.
You start Dimeo, you can hear each other in the Oculus thing.
And then you realize actually, if you're in like a room together with the Oculus thing,
it's a different thing than the multiplayer inside the game, even though both of them use
the Oculus API.
So now you have to get out of the game, get out of the room that you are in the Oculus
sort of social thing, create a new one inside the game.
And then you're like, you have to send the secret code of that room to your friends.
So then you take off the headset and you try to WhatsApp them the good thing.
I'm getting some questions.
Yeah.
And this is why I use the browser.
So when is this going to go away?
When can we actually like get into VR without a PhD in computer science?
Exactly.
So when is that going to go away?
Well, that's what I'm trying to do.
And I think that some, here's my guess.
I would say I don't really trust meta to solve it.
I don't really trust HTC either or Valve.
I think their track record shows that they're not going to solve for it.
I would say Apple is one that might be able to solve it.
And then my company were trying to solve it.
And the answer is the most boring one.
It's going to be a very boring answer.
But the solution is just we have a bunch of developers and we're just trying it all day
long and we're just solving those pain points one by one.
And it's long and boring, but polishing the edges off and making it smooth is just long
and boring work.
And that's just what we do.
And there's not really any other around that.
So yeah, that's, and once this is solved, then yes, certainly once you can just grab
the headset, put it on the experience of anything in VR as opposed to like this 35
minutes long process.
Then yeah, I think it's going to brutally change the adoption curve.
And we can already see that because the very young ones are spending a lot of time in it.
So that would be my takeaway.
Okay, I want to ask a related question.
I have no insight information just where I read from.
I'm going to have a scoble which bring later into the course.
Apple, and I think it's now been delayed with what they were going to do.
But their big idea was or rumors were they were developing the super cool AR glasses.
And it's Apple.
So they're going to be awesome, but turns out they're not going to watch them this year.
But they were explicitly saying, you know, the way we get to make sure that we're going
to do the mass adoption is AR, not VR.
Because I guess you can still see your day, and I'll be more like a pair of glasses, not
a big book headset.
What do you think about that?
Yeah.
My sort of takeaway on that is, okay, so there's a few things.
The first one is I think people love to say that because AR is easier to understand.
They're looking for a compelling narrative.
And AR is not most of when people think of AR as kind of like a phone that's trapped
to your face.
So you can just see your phone open.
So you don't really have to sit down and think it through of like, what is it?
Is a radically new paradigm shift in the way we use computer to understand AR.
It's like pretty easy to understand.
So to me, I think the whole debate is actually kind of missing the point.
And I know people love to ask me that question, but to me, it feels a little bit like as if
in the early 80s, people would ask me, do you think?
Do you think, I don't know, like facts or cassettes are going to win?
Like do you think we're going to send each other data by printing it out from the computer
or do you think we'll keep it in a digital form and put it on a cassette and send it
to each other?
Like what do you think is going to be the best way to send data around?
And turn it out, none of those view would have been correct.
It's just that those views are easier to translate into what we already know in the real world.
But the one that turned out to be true, it turned out to be none of those.
And so I think here it's kind of like the same thing where when you go and actually
ask the people that use it every day, AR or VR, you realize that the line is very blurred.
And that's also my personal belief, which is very soon people are just going to kind
of forget that AR and VR are two different things anyway.
Because some of the things we need to improve the VR experience look a lot like AR.
Like for instance, here's one thing that you've certainly experienced.
When you put on the VR headset, like there's my laptop right now for me, the fact that
I can just like move and sort of bash into the laptop and break it, that's a big issue.
So the way to solve that is to actually be able to, when I get close to the laptop, I
can see that though, and I can see it exactly like in real life.
And there are many ways to that.
You have some displays that are transparent and they can turn on and off the transparency.
You have pass through where you have cameras that we project what happens in the real world
in the VR headset.
But my sort of, the TLDR is, I think it's a false dichotomy that people like to make
because they feel slightly disappointed by the adoption curve of VR.
And they say, no, no, no, but the field is interesting.
VR has not taken off as fast as we thought it would.
But actually the thing afterwards is going to take off really fast and that thing is AR.
My take is that lack nuance and the real IT is more nuanced and the real IT is actually
those things are going to become kind of the same thing.
And we want to really even think of them as separate stuff as time goes on and as adoption
continues to grow.
Okay.
Thank you.
All right, let's talk about present day adoption now in on cyber in for my view living in this
is the one that so far has the most of option.
Okay, people use it to show their NFTs, right?
So you can't imagine a more like native set of people than people who have NFTs or can
create NFTs and I said, oh, I would like to show my NFT and a matter of words, made out
of NFTs.
I would even say even within that, the what I've seen is the fastest to jump on it are
artists, creators like the most sophisticated NFT people are even the collectors, right?
They're the creators.
And so because I've had many discussions and people have to do this and I'm working
to do this.
I mean, the ones who say yes instantly require no convincing or NFT artists, which you know,
these are like the apex NFT naders.
So that part's going well, that seems clear.
Where do you see more adoption by less apex digital NFT naders?
What do you think comes next?
Yeah, I think that like one one thing that's very interesting about on saber and how it's
got an adoption across like this space specifically is that it's a tool that allows people to
build their own world.
And kind of like the analogy I have is like almost like when you were a kid and like you
were imagining these things and imagining yourself building castles at home out of like
pillows or whatnot, like this is kind of the same feeling that you have whenever you curate
the on-saber space, like the idea without saber is to make it as easy as possible for
anyone.
You really anyone from a newcomer into the space to a gamer maybe but definitely not
the 74 gamers to go and build worlds.
And I think that world building has been popularized by a bunch of labs like the like the sims,
for example, or of course, like within the more gamers type of spheres, roadblocks and
Minecraft and whatnot.
But it hasn't gone to my mother.
My mother hasn't done world building.
I think that on-saber and like what we're trying to achieve is a tool that allows anyone
to be able to build worlds and allows for 3D to be kind of democratized across the hands
of everyone, not just 3D modelers or gamers that have been able to like play around with
world building at 3D but really anyone at all.
So I think that sure like I think that the space, the web 3 space is a lot of early adopters.
I think that the fact that artists and collectors but artists even more impressively like a lot
of the artists we have in this space today are not like big like are not crypto G's or
I come from from like the Bitcoin days or whatnot.
They're not necessarily the biggest technology native people like or but they're able to
go and build with on-saber and curate their experiences.
So I think it's very encouraging that they are able to go and create more than it's a
worry that like we don't have enough people curating worlds or whatnot.
I think what's very interesting about the web 3 spaces that you have people from all
boards like you have people that are tech native, that are crypto native, that are not at all,
that have always been doing painting, have always been doing something else.
It's not like it's easy to pinpoint what kind of tech scales or capabilities like someone
web 3 has.
So I think that having adoption early and like that kind of a space just is very telling
of where this could go and I am very confident that the moment we are able to go and just
make it easier for people outside of web 3 to come in and use those tools and have 3D
democratized the way we have for artists and collectors in the web 3 space until now.
That's the moment where we are going to see like more adoption across people.
I think everyone wants to be a world builder.
And I don't know anyone that would answer a no to the question would you like to get back
to the imagination you had whenever you were a kid and building these castles at home with
pills.
So I think that if we're able to give back this effect and this feeling to people all
across the web 3 space, the moment we have easier tools to onboard other people outside
of web 3, the moment is that we're going to have more adoption clearly.
So I mean, I think it's up to us to number one, communicate better as to like what can
be done with this tool and like these immersive tools on the web.
Like that you can come in build your own world slash universe, share it with anyone with a
link and anyone across the world can come and enjoy it in the same way.
Now it's up to us to first communicate that and number two just build the right tooling
for people to be able to come in obviously like we don't expect to be hidden behind a
MetaMask connect forever like MetaMask is as much as they've been doing good stuff for
this space like our is a very hard tool to use for most people.
Web 3 browsers in general are pretty hard to use for most people and call it a wallet
even is pretty confusing to like the people, my friends and the people who aren't in web
3.
So I think it's up to us to just build the right tooling.
Okay, I'm going to switch now to the not the far future.
I'm pretty sure the far future minimums know given the pace of technological development
happening.
I assume the AIs will have taken over by them.
Let's go for the medium future.
It's 2023.
Let's say 2030.
We'll again start with Charlie in broadly the field we're talking about.
What does the world look like then?
How different is it from today?
How what should we expect?
I'm well aware all of us are just guessing.
But at least you're in the field working on real problems so your guesses are forged
from some actual experiences as opposed to other people who are just guessing.
So give us your view of 2030.
So I think I was like going back to what Ryan was just saying about the tooling.
Right now we are at the skeleton of infrastructure for Web 3 which you do need to be reasonably
text savvy to make your way through.
There's a lot of fleshing out to do.
I think by the time we're hitting 2030 that's going to be done to a pretty significant degree.
I mean the way that I think about metaverse is that it's like various digital layers on
top of the physical world.
And the first kind of key point that we need to move to is where it feels like there isn't
really a division between physical identity and digital identity, your physical life experience,
digital life experience.
So I would see 2030 as being like we've reached a point where the technology is good enough,
accessible enough where we're not thinking about the switch from physical into digital,
especially when it comes to socializing.
And I think again like going back to the eight to 12 year olds, this is already their reality.
They come home from school and then they're in like audio based, audio based like social
platform by Fortnite for example.
And they're just like carrying on with their brands from their day at school.
There's no consideration that like I'm switching from physical identity to digital identity.
So I think it's getting to the point where that is really widespread.
I think there'll be a lot of development still to do going back to what Maxime is working
on about when you're in the virtual space, you want to leave it where that has actually
improved your quality of life.
I think that's going to be a lot of work to continue to do that.
But I think the like the clear division will have gone or dissolved by that time.
Yeah.
Okay.
So I agree it's always a hard to do this kind of prediction because you're kind of sitting
yourself up in a way to look like an idiot because as always you know you miss some stuff
and then people look back.
But what I can do.
It's seven years from now.
We're safe.
Yeah.
Right.
So but still like you know we have a company you and I and we're trying to we're investing
our time and money.
And so when I can answer is well where are we investing and how does like how are like
what are some believe that for that where we have put some skin the game basically.
And where do we put some skin in the game is.
You know I was on a flight to the US recently and Stuart is started stuck with me and I
told her I work in VR and told me how my little nephew is super young he's using that
all day.
And like that's like that's like a new kind of question that now I have very often with
people where VR is the thing that someone very young in their family is using a lot.
And it's almost like an alternative to using a console.
And so in seven years from now those 12 to like 15 years old they're going to be old
enough to make their own purchase and and and and buy their own content.
And there's a few things that are going to change that are pretty fundamental.
And so I think it's useful to share that because I think many people are ignoring that in the
industry.
As you know VR makes people sick you get motion sickness or people have a hard time
understanding having like special awareness or that there is a social acceptance issue
where you look weird if you are your headset.
So what is interesting is all those young people that are going up with VR right now
they won't suffer from those.
And so in 2030 what I see is a generation of now very young adults that are looking for
better hardware, better software, better experiences.
And the other thing that I see is your the opportunity window in like traditional internet
is closing very fast.
Like if you're building a nap and putting it on the app store you're competing against
so many people so much money so many momentum so much stuff.
It's like you want to make it here's a company I recently invested in that does dating in
VR.
Well if you want to do dating in like the real world there is like 20 different apps and
they're all owned by like a few gigantic billion dollar groups and it's like really hard to
compete in the VR world.
There's like a bunch of kids and and they're building a bunch of apps and like that's where
the new space for opportunity is and so seven years more people opportunity are sort of
clocked up in the traditional digital world and so VR becomes one where you can send those
opportunities.
Now our diet is back into crypto as a way to sort of finish this answer.
This is where crypto and VR are hyper hyper like super relevant to each other where basically
it's going to be super hard to convince Microsoft or EA or or any of those very large game
publishers to switch to crypto for their games right because what like they have nothing
like frankly they have nothing to they're already making pretty much as much money as
they possibly can right.
And and the premise of crypto is more so a threat to their business model than something
that is going to help them.
It's like Apple like Apple is never going to allow you to build a great great wallet
on iOS like I'm strongly strongly doubt that because crypto to some extent is threatening
some of what enables Apple to have built this manipulate over time.
Now if you look at VR people like me where I have the opposite problem we like we've
not built anything we're starting from complete scratch and we're looking for people that
are super eager super excited.
And if anything if we can find a way to align a large number of people to collaborate on
stuff in a decentralized manner such that we can come up and try to sort of all group
together against those gigantic monopolies of course we're going to welcome it with open
arms right.
And so the other thing that I see for VR is that all of those things that you see on
the fringes of sort of society right where Apple might not have many much stuff to gain
integrating crypto into the iPhone but I have a lot of things to gain integrating crypto
for it because now all of a sudden I'm attracting users that prior to that I had not any access
to I'm attracting content creators that perked that they had zero access to and and my closing
thought on this will be the following.
I believe that software paradigm are often enabled by new hardware and those things they
come sort of hand in hand.
One famous example would be the iMac which we tend to forget is called the iMac because
it stands for internet Macintosh and you have to remember that back then it was the first
computer that shipped with high speeds of modern ports web browser inside the OS it
shipped with web browser inside a ship with an OS level SDK for connecting for writing
apps that connects to the internet and so it helped their hardware right because it gave
them access to a new growing market and it helped this new set of protocols because now
they had a dedicated device that embraced them.
In my case it's pretty similar I have a lot to gain by embracing those new standards and
trying to accrue value with them over time and I think those standards are going to have
a very hard time convincing team cook to make a great crypto experience on the iPhone
and disrupt himself and his own app store but they're going to have a very easy time convincing
me to make my VR headset deeply deeply integrated down to the OS level with crypto to those
with the micro addictions.
That's very interesting.
Can I view for how you play 30?
Yeah I think one thing that I would have never guessed is like how much beauty and culture
and belonging would be democratizing I think that my prediction for 2030 is like we build
this new space on the web where people can belong and live culture and find beauty every
single day.
I think it's important for us to just keep on focusing on making sure that it's open
and that people can freely come in and leave and not be chained by any type of centralized
power.
My prediction is that we actually get there through the power of culture because now
that all the creators are on our side I think it's going to be hard for the centralized
systems to go and build as cool experiences or as beautiful experiences online as they
can be by this army of decentralized collaboration this army of really really cool creators from
all across the world.
So my guess is it keeps on going and the decentralized web very soon is just the coolest
place ever to discover content and to live like truly live experiences rather than just
be consumed by them.
So I do predict that we'll get there.
There's a lot of people working on it.
There's a lot of good intentions.
So I believe.
Okay, I'm going to ask the audience to start sending questions to the UNIC team which will
feed them to me and I'll ask them of you and when you give your questions let us know if
they are general or for a specific person.
And if you'd like us to address them to someone specifically or just for the panel
and what we want to answer.
But I'll wait for those to come in.
Like I'll stay with Ryan since we're talking.
Like are we going to see ready player one type things in the next 15, 20 years where
we're I mean genuinely living your way.
I want to speak to a normal person.
And I say oh none of us right.
They imagine already player one a fully realistic fully immersive full VR economy.
And then they look at what's happening.
Obviously it doesn't exist right now.
And then there's maybe some disappointed is actually what's happening.
What's happening now?
Is that going to happen?
Is that even realistic to think about?
Absolutely.
I think that the hardest thing to get past is probably like culture and having people
want to do or live experiences online rather than just like visit them or like be pretty
much absent while experiencing them.
I think that tech is going to get better at an exponential rate.
And technically for sure I think there's going to be a way to do all these photo realistic
experiences that I've seen examples of things that are pretty mind blowing today already.
So I don't think it's going to be it's that far off or like that hard to do.
Now how is it going to happen?
I have no clue.
I think that my position on this has always been to just wait and see what people want
to do with these things.
My perspective is that I'm going to keep on having very strong deep, deep like connection
with the community and what people actually want to do and how they want to experience
these immersive spaces online.
And they should just keep on building from there.
So I think that yeah, we could really play one.
Something similar to really play one is something that's pretty much doable in a few years.
But I don't know if it's what people really want to do.
But I know it's how to ask for the next thing and the next thing.
So we'll see.
I'm going to ask you why we wait for the questions coming because I think this is partially a
hard word topic because basically, and I'll say this for the audience, the most common
thing that I have in my Discord DMs is Ryan yelling at me about how we're making our spaces
to make performance better for normal people.
And this is, I log in on with a fancy graphic card and a big desktop.
And obviously, Ryan's correct because a lot of people are logging in on phones or on the
computers.
And that's what today's experience is that are nowhere close to being photo-rosed.
They are not in the bad way, but sort of cartoonish, right?
They're never on photo-rulism.
They're never on what people see when they watch the movie.
And we still struggle with performance.
Is this something that GPUs will take care of it in a decade or are we waiting 30 years
for this?
Or what does the curve look like?
Sure.
Okay, that's an excellent question.
All right, so the short answer is actually yes.
If you just have to be like a little patient and actually we're going to go there and surprisingly
fast.
For the people that are interested in stuff like neural radiance fields, which are a type
of neural networks for 3D rendering, those are showing incredible results and really fast
and improving really quickly.
And there are a lot of people in the field that like me believe that those might be a
very short path toward photo-realism.
Another thing to note is in general AI slash neural networks enable rendering as vastly,
and improve the performance of rendering and GPUs are just kind of by themselves getting
better and better.
So the short answer is you are certainly getting there, that is for sure.
How long is it going to take?
I would say that within a decade it's going to be pretty wild, how different those things
are going to look.
Now sort of my, and I'll just, I'll give the short version of it, but my slightly longer
answer is I would actually question the premise of the question.
And I will actually say, well, do photo-realism really matter?
And I would question that a lot.
And I will say the following.
Picsar is an incredible example of how you can convey emotion, meaning and beauty without
photo-realism, if you just focus your effort on the right stuff.
And there's a story, if people are familiar with me, I have to let's say a million times,
so they may be super bored about it.
But one simple story is when, it's a little more of a bit at the beginning, but when people
die, the first thing that happens is that their eyes dry off.
So when they're, because they are dried off, you don't have like any light reflection in
your eyes.
And as a result of that, the human brain evolved such that when you talk to someone, the first
thing that your brain does is look for those light reflection in their eyes.
Because if they are missing, it means the person is very, very sick or dying or maybe
already dead.
And so that's a kind of built deep inside of like the back of your brain.
And thus, if I show you a 3D rendering of a world and you're talking with people, and
I just remove the light reflections in their eyes, it's going to feel really uncanny and
you're really not going to have a good time.
If you're going to feel really weird.
And those things, I think, are going to have quite a big impact knowing what details are
needed for people to have this sort of comfortable feeling.
But the overall look and photo-realism, I would strongly sort of push back and say that it's
necessary and I think you are just a good example.
So my overall takeaway is people in the industry, like people making anime or Pixar or to some
extent VR chat, although I think we're still very far from a guru of Kuwaiti Nude, I think
are kind of proof that photo-realism isn't really needed as much as people think it is
as long as you nail the right details.
And you might think that, yeah, but all the rooms, they look bad in VR.
Like a virtual cafes, most of them VR, I can't feel good in them, I'm sure with photo-realism
it would feel better.
And again, I would, as I said, push back against that once more and say the following, must
cafes that I've been to feel good.
One of the reasons that I feel good in it is because it's built upon literally like hundreds
of years of interior designers iterating on how to make a place feel comfortable.
And it turns out what makes you comfortable in VR in the real world are two different
things.
And you don't have that kind of like care and experience and for VR where people have just
spent like 20,000 hours trying to find how to make people comfortable in virtual spaces.
And I think part of the revolution is not necessarily having it be photo-realistic, but
just sort of as an industry learning how to make those spaces more comfortable.
Yeah, no, I mean look for the foreseeable future.
And I'm 24 by 24 pixel pump, right?
So it works fine for emotion and identity and branding.
But it's also, I want to call this to an objective truth.
It's not like we tested the photo-realistic and decided to do the work, we just can't
do it.
So it's extremely convenient if we concluded the photo-realistic's not any good.
This is like me concluding that thinking of basketball is a good thing.
I think I was going to dunk a basketball anyway, so it's better that I concluded that
it's not a good thing, right?
So I do think people wonder about this, right?
And you can say, I don't want to pick someone, I can watch Pixar, but I can also watch a
regular movie.
Right, we also have regular movies, we don't just have animated movies, right?
I mean, I've question or asked why I'm before this session, as we started this session.
I actually don't know the answer, I don't think anyone's know the answer.
We could have done this on the campus as an avatar, with voice.
You know, there'd be three avatars standing in campus talking, four of us, sorry.
Is it better?
Really worse.
That we're projected on a two-dimensional screen and we can see your faces of this,
I mean, in my mind, but yours.
I don't know, I don't know the answer, right?
I know which one's better.
And I mean, I'm sure we'll do both, right?
We'll try both over time.
But it's a very interesting question to me.
And I've thought about this the whole course.
I sit in these sessions and these sessions are Zoom.
And so we're projecting a Zoom into a 3D world.
You're like, well, yeah, I'll add to that.
I'll add one thing to that is that, yeah, we have been projected as a 2D on a speed.
But I've been dancing with a bunch of people in the crowd for a while and like we did a
bunch of different dances and the flash mode.
So I think my answer to this is that it will only take trying things out with people and
seeing what works and what doesn't work, et cetera.
There's no way to go and get the magic recipe of what is better to do a university course
in an immersive space.
Maybe in the future, I will get back to this to feel the real emotions of people.
Maybe we'll have face tracking technologies that do it well.
I don't know.
But I think that our goal and I think our mission of all the people experimenting in
this is to actually experiment and try to see what does make sense, what does catch
with people, what doesn't catch with people and try to navigate in that way.
But yeah, if one thing I can say.
I agree, we're going to expand.
But literally in this box, there's one of us who is not photo-realistic and that works
and three of you were photo-realistic.
And I was wondering the whole time wondering, which one's better?
I mean, if not, like I look at you and say, oh, really?
I wish Maxine would disappear and become an avatar.
I like seeing you.
And so the interesting question, OK, we have a couple of questions that come in.
The first one I'm sending to Charlie because I don't expect you to have an official answer
to this.
But I think it's a fair question.
For the general panel, but since you had mentioned all your cousins, I'm going to go
to you, what about the mental health aspects of eight to 10-year-olds or even 12-year-olds
going directly into VR after school and not doing normal kid things like playing outside?
Oh, I guess you're...
I mean, yes, it's a big question.
When you're thinking about what's happening in terms of brain chemistry, is there a reason
that they're impacting their mental health negatively by feeling like they have a safe
space to socially interact so they can be themselves, where they can fully explore their
identity that maybe they might not have outside in a physical environment.
It's like it's such a sweeping generalization.
I think there's a lot that we've learned from Web2's social media about the impact of Web2
on mental health, especially where your identity and how much people like your identity in
the digital world becomes kind of currency for status.
We've seen that that's a problem.
We have the opportunity now where we can be building out Web3 with all of the learnings
of Web2 severely fucked up when it comes to mental health and started to try to address
those problems.
But I think it's a very like a cliched question.
It's going to be healthier for a child to be participating in X space versus Y space
because that's how I grew up.
We don't really have the data to support that that's the case.
I certainly know a lot of people in the younger generation who have the opportunity to explore
who they are via an alter ego where they aren't subject to the judgment of their peers, the
fear of being documented and posted on Web2 social media by their peers.
They can really start to experiment in a way that's become progressively harder with photo
and video based social media.
Arguably being avatar based in a VR space or within a game is healthier because they
get to do all these things that have been becoming more and more socially restrictive
over time.
I think there's just so much nuance to this that gets missed when it's like, well, I
grew up like this and I think it's bad that these kids aren't growing up the same way.
Maxim, do you want to comment on this too?
I think I have a very similar perspective.
I will add, I think it's a great question to ask but even more importantly, so as you
know, I'm sure a lot of you in the audience listening to this are considering going into
crypto.
I think the people prior to us, people building social media as we've been there in 2000 or
computers in the 90s might have had a path, a path for not having built a very strong
sort of answers to those questions because it was hard to prove that digital world could
have an adverse effect.
I think now that we've seen that actually they can have an adverse effect, no one is
like, oh, I'm so happy I spent 20 hours on Instagram this week.
Not only do we observe that, I think it's good to be critical and my pushback to being
critical would be very smart to surely most of the greatest cool stuff I've learned and
discovered about myself and that sort of became core part of who I am in my identity.
That was through virtual worlds.
So I do act as hard as I can to try to identify what could go wrong and try to fix it but
I'm not to miss that actually we can fix all of the stuff that might go wrong.
I'm going to also want to comment on this.
I mean, like everything has been said, like they try to do a maxim, I don't know what
I could have really.
It's interesting because like I hear in my like natural reactions, only that sounds
worrisome and then I also remember when I was a boy guy, there was like all types of anxiety
about video games and I spent my teenage years like every afternoon like my friends
and sometimes you play basketball or whatever and sometimes we just send out my video games
all afternoon.
And as far as I can tell, everyone grew up to be a responsible adult and like that was
fine.
Like I mean, but if you listen to what people were saying then, I don't know, it was going
to be the end of the next generation of the total disaster and it was fine.
Like everyone kind of grew up and had a perfectly real life and none of us seemed to have been
negatively affected by video games and now of course the studies come out and say like
maybe actually video games are good for you and you know who knows, not straight or but
like it certainly wasn't anything resembling the panic that for some reason if you're playing
say our PlayStation or what have you, things were going to go wildly wrong in your life
like quite the opposite.
It was a worst mutual.
Okay, I have another quite general question which is hard but I think it's a good question.
How do you see the metaverse, we can take this in reverse order and start with Ryan.
How do you see the metaverse impacting society and specifically what steps should be taken
to ensure it is inclusive and equitable for all?
That's a very broad scope to play.
Yeah, it's a very, very good question.
I think to my point of my prediction within seven years, like I would have never guessed
that online I would be able to see so much beauty every single day.
I think by scrolling through my Twitter feed or going to on cyber like every single day
I'm confronted with really, really cool stuff, new stuff I didn't know, art, creativity and
I think if anything what the metaverse has managed to accomplish until now for like a
short, a small group of people is to like democratize beauty and to make sure that people can access
culture and art in a way that they couldn't before.
I think I personally like would access art just once every month, every month and a half
whenever I would go to a gallery or go to like I don't know a museum or whatnot.
But nowadays like every single day like I see new creations being put on on on on on
on Twitter being shared.
They see news that new artists I didn't know.
I get I get addicted to like certain art styles that I didn't know I liked.
So I think that that's something that one positive that it managed to do.
I think that one thing that we really have to do to make sure that this keeps on going
is accessibility and to make sure that any creative from all across the world or any
art and joy or any person in general because we are all creators by default.
We are all board creators.
We are all board collectors.
We're all born art and joyers and like and and I think that the one thing we need to do
is to make sure that the the platforms are as accessible as possible to everyone.
And that those platforms don't become the exact same platforms we're using now that
are not accessible to everyone and that can love people out of their own accounts, etc.
So I think that's one thing we need to do.
But overall I think that if we managed to do that through the principles of decentralization,
we get to a really, really good result that we I start seeing every single day today.
I know a lot of people around me as well are seeing which is the market sizing belonging,
the market sizing culture, the market sizing beauty.
And I think it's really important for humans to be able to to be confronted with that as
well.
Sorry.
Anyone else want to thank you for that?
Yeah, I can jump in on that.
As I'm working specifically in digital identity, there's a huge way of responsibility when
we're thinking about like diversity and representation.
You know, anybody that's building in the like habitat space, identity space.
You know, I think the first thing that's important, you know, where you know, building
web three now, we already have a much more diverse cross section of builders than we
had in the earlier stages of the internet.
So the first thing that's important thing, especially if you're creating around identity
is making sure that everybody who is contributing to how that builds out and how you're representing
people that you haven't, you know, you have a very diverse cross section of opinions and
cultures that are coming into the mix when you, you know, figure out how you're building
that out.
And then the other piece, as Ryan said, you know, everybody is fundamentally creative.
I mean, we've just seen over the last year how AI has started to democratize creativity,
right?
You don't need to be amazing at drawing to become an artist or become a creator.
So I think, you know, for you as a human to like, you know, fulfill the full joy of the
human experience, you need to be able to create stuff.
So there is also a responsibility to democratize access to creation and technology is making
that increasingly easy.
So I guess those are the two pieces that I'm focused on given that we're building for
identity and we're building for allowing people to easily create and customize their identity.
Yeah, if I can just finish this stuff, like there's a, there's a quote I read in Rick Ruben's
book, lately, Rick Ruben is a big, very famous music producer who's worked with people like
it was was that the inception of Dev Jam in the 90s and worked with every single artist
you can think of.
And like there's one quote of his that really, really struck by me and like my mission on
with on saver and I'll read it now.
Regardless of whether or not we're formally making art, we're all living as artists.
We perceive, perceive filter and collect data, then curate and experience for ourselves and
others based on this information set.
Whether we do this consciously or unconsciously by the mere fact of being alive, we are active
participants in the ongoing process of creation.
And I think that's really, really important as like to what we're doing in web three and
how we're able to just like bring this flame of creativity back to every single person.
That's the participant.
Great.
I have a question that I don't know what an answer to what I feel professionally obligated
to ask.
Maxine, what is your headshot coming out?
Jane from the group.
Okay.
Unfortunity, we're enough communicating data community yet.
However, you can email me and I'm adding people to our I'll find better at least all the time.
Write me a short blurb about yourself where you come out of your and I'll do my best to
add you to one of our spots.
There's a second part of the question I suspect we're going to be answering and I'll ask
you also.
Does your head said have a name yet?
What, sorry?
Does it have a name yet?
Oh, a name yet.
You can follow me on Twitter, I'll be announcing stuff pretty soon.
But sorry again, we've hired too many people from Apple and so we took that from them which
I tried to be here to tell you about all the stuff.
Absolutely respect that but I had to shoot my shot on behalf of the studio audience.
There's a question that I think I can answer.
You can expect more avatars as NFTs for all integration and I think the answer is yes but
probably I don't know.
Two or three months away on various things so we're working on it and expect cool things
happening there.
Is that, we're here with that Ryan as an answer?
Yeah, totally, totally.
Again, as for everything we do, everything is experimental.
We very often do QA in broad and so this was one of the examples where we just pushed
avatars as quick as we could with a very optimized system so on the web right now we could render
like a thousand avatars next to each other on an iPhone.
We had to just have one to be able to achieve that feat and then be able to optimize more
to be able to add more I think within next two months yeah we'll be able to have many
more avatars and truly have like identity in the form of avatars within Unsamer.
Okay, we are at time so I wanted to thank all three of our panelists for taking the time
to meet with us, very much appreciate your insights.
We will turn this into an NFT soon and I think soon beyond that soon we'll have our better
organizational model and how we display all these both on the campus in the thirties case
and also how people can find them on the web because like this panel there have been a lot
of great panels and sessions and I think these are great things for people to watch whether
they were here today at specifically this time and so we want we think that's an important
part of helping to educate the space so I appreciate you doing that.
We'll let you know once they're minted you can share the music we'll find a model where
the content comes if people can open mint them into their wallet if you want to keep this
for austerity sake making it immutable so you can show your grandchildren how wrong your
predictions for 2031 and a model what we want so thank you very much.
Thank you.
Thank you so much.
There was awesome.
Thanks so much.
Yeah thank you for having us does a pleasure.