Hello and good evening.
Thank you everyone for joining us for this conversation with three of the leading artists
in the NFT space about generative art.
My name is Anika.
I'm the moderator.
I'm a writer.
Yeah, I started by writing about social media and art and ended up with NFTs.
And yeah, we have three artists here with us tonight.
Helena, Matt, I, Xcels.
I, all of you are very familiar with the names, the faces and their work.
Yeah, as just mentioned prior, there are three of the leading artists in this space.
They have created work before NFTs.
They created NFTs during the hype or created generative art before the hype.
They lived through the hype and now they're still here.
So I'm very honored that all three of us are with us tonight.
And the first thing I would like to speak with you about because I sit in a gyro space
right now, which we open in December.
It's one of the main streets in Berlin.
It's a collaboration with VIRS.
We named a generative abstraction and it's quite interesting because a lot of people
just walk by and come in and the show is titled generative abstraction.
And in your, I mean, for this talk, it just says generative artists.
And yeah, when people come in here, it's basically people who are not familiar really with NFTs
and what generative art is.
So how do you explain to people who are not part of the NFT space what you actually do?
Who would like to start?
I could start.
Okay, Matt, go ahead.
Yeah, it's a funny thing to explain because I'll answer this in the context of a couple
of years ago before everything sort of changed a little bit with NFTs and blockchain and
crypto and everything.
But even then it was very difficult to explain because first you kind of have to explain
that you're creating art with a computer and then you have to explain you're creating
art with code quite often.
And then people tend to be like, how do you make art with code and then you have to kind
of explain how you can use code to draw lines or to make shapes or sounds or something.
And it becomes this like 20 minute long discussion just to get to the basics of it.
So sometimes nowadays I'll quite often just say artist or I'll just say digital artist
or computer artist because generative art is sort of a can of worms for a lot of discussions.
And more recently with crypto and NFT, it's also changed again.
It's sometimes depending on who you're chatting with, if they are familiar with NFTs and crypto
and you say you're a generative artist, no matter whether you do or do not engage with
NFTs, sometimes their first reaction is, oh, all you do is NFTs or is that like what
you do now?
And there's a whole world of generative art outside of that as well.
So it's sort of, it has been a tricky thing to sort of wrap up in a short conversational
small talk sort of way.
And it's even more complicated now I would say.
But when you do go into this with some people that are not familiar, they quite often they're
really sort of stunned or they're like surprised by it.
A lot of people, they know what code is and they know what some of these kind of ideas
are and they can put it together once somebody explains it to them and they can say, well,
that's kind of cool.
Yeah.
I bet there's more kind of words.
As soon as you mentioned the word NFTs and everyone's like, oh, there's still a thing
I thought they are dead.
Then you have the next 30 minute conversation going.
Thank you.
Who would like to speak next?
Hitzel or Helena?
Yeah, I can add a little bit because I'm sort of on the GSN territory because I was
lumped, well, still lumped with AI art, which is another kind of warm.
But I consider myself more and more generative artists this day because like Matt said, I
mean, at the end of the day, like people who work with the code who write their own code
who in case of AI make their own data sets or tweak their own models, that basically
makes us kind of like generative slash computational artists.
And that's the category I like to put myself in.
I think something interesting has happened with AI in recent months with like mid-journey
and Dolly and stuff is that the definition of like an AI artist that works with AI has
also sort of been shifted in this public perception.
Yeah, the territory of AI art was claimed by the prompt base AI, but that's not the
kind of like story.
Yeah.
Yeah, my case, I think is tiny bit more complicated when it comes to explaining why the art with
computers, there's nobody does it in my country.
I'm like one of the only ones like I can count five artists that works with computers to
create art in my country.
And this is like a tiny town where only three million people and I've gone to a few talks
and I think people can get that this is another tool.
I've tried my best to simplify the terms and just demonstrate that I can create with
emotion and with sticks and stones and generative art or the medium which is social signer in
my case.
It's just another way for me to find a way to express just like others do with dance
and music, which is more predominant and kind of one.
I like to say that I like to replicate or simulate what's around me using math and using
just in general like geometry or the errors that you can find in code create something
different just to say I found to express what is generative art and what I do.
Thank you.
We had the conversation more often that you said in your country that's very few artists
who actually work with code and in the NFT space.
This question goes again to all three of us.
How did you or when did you know you would like to become an artist or that you are an
artist and then how did you get to the part ways that working with code?
Well, I started with photography back when I was living in Toronto.
I was there doing different jobs like working in as a dot walker.
I work in a pixel place and in Shisha Varr like so many places.
But I really love just going for a walk and taking photos of buildings or like how the
lights will come through like structures and even from the trees.
I think I've always been in love with being fascinated with how light goes into tiny places
and where you can imagine.
I started looking for programs to study.
I went through architectural technology.
I was really interested in urban planning partly because my partner at the time was studying
that and I used to sneak in to her classes and being really just about fixing issues that
can help people live in a better way like with landscape design or you know all of this
like subjects that this career includes.
That career was really expensive so I changed to I try to find other ways to learn about
computer and design, designing plans and like buildings and I look for programs in this
online courses and I found computer science and I just I couldn't stop reading about it
and learning how colors can contain information.
And that information can be used to create other things including the tools that we used
to make art.
So I was really inspired.
I was just really trying to become someone else and being able to come back to my country
with something.
So it was a mix of photography, architecture, love and like just practice.
I used to read a lot even if I wasn't taking the course because they were still really
expensive.
I haven't finished school but I think I taught myself how to do things and how to manage
them.
I think what made me fall in love with it the most was the lack of control I had over what
I was doing.
I used to imagine like cities within like all of this patterns that were like at first glance
you think it's like nothing is rubbish but if you look at it with imagination like you
can see tiny nations or cities and were like just something else.
So I felt like oh okay so this is like this is my thing like seeing things through abstraction.
So that's part of like how I started.
Thank you for sharing your story.
I would like to share the story next with us.
I've been a professional software developer for a long time but also more lighted in art
and with like computational art I started accidentally in a sense that at work I was
doing some stuff with neural networks and then I decided to try it with my own art.
So I was lucky enough that I had like heaps of digital photographs from my food styling
moonlighting so I used them to kind of train networks, neural networks from scratch and
like Excel said I mean it's kind of fascinating when from something like photography you get
into something else and actually like I pivoted to the artist's career more than five years
ago because I was totally fascinated by the how AI and neural network can elevate your
artistic voice in a sense.
I never got it with the analog art to be honest.
Sorry I just wanted to ask one question.
Did you just say you're not good with analog art?
No, it's not like I'm good or not good but it's just like too mainstream to average.
I wanted, I mean I like to do like unique interesting stuff and like in watercolor you
basically it's like hard to do it.
So I mean I hit the artistic book at some point and AI actually helped me to kind of like
break through.
Okay, thank you sorry for interrupting.
I just was curious because sometimes if people come by and they don't know about NFTs and
then the question is always like yeah do they have a background in like physical art or
did they start straight away with code because it's so hard for people who are not familiar
with artists using the digital space to imagine that you start out with code.
That's also why I ask you how did you get started as an artist.
Many artists say, many artists say and that's always my first question in interview.
When did you know you are an artist or would you like to become an artist?
Any artist say I love drawing as a kid and that's what I like to do in my life.
I mean I was good at drawing but I was like not thinking I would want to become an artist
so I thought maybe that's different for artists and that's maybe why I'm not an artist because
I didn't think that as a kid but I don't know.
Matt?
I mean when I was a kid I loved drawing but I don't know if I had the sole vision of like
I'm going to be an artist in my life kind of thing but also I think part of that was just
you know you're not really quite often.
It's not always seen as like something that you could do like you know people are like
okay here's the list of possible jobs that you should look into and very rarely is digital
artists using code ever on there.
So I think one of the things like for me at least here's my sort of little thing is I
think it was around 2014 or so that I started to learn about these kind of ideas of generative
art.
I think at the time was like really familiar with the whole sort of history of things but
I was just starting to use code for something that was more artistic than what I had done
before and I really like kind of fell in love with that.
I just wanted to use the skills I was learning with code and JavaScript and graphics programming
and apply those to just making art because before that I had this kind of winding path
where in university I studied film and media thinking you know really something to do with
film would be really interesting but it kind of I came to realize it's not really an easy
career.
It's a lot of struggling, it's a lot of just brutal hours and I didn't really want to go
through some of that and at the end of it I felt like a lot of the work I was learning
to do in film was not always kind of you know my own and so I like doing these little projects
even at university I was just doing code and I was like doing little games and little graphical
toys and things like that with either Java at the time or sometimes using flash using
ActionScript and yeah I guess it wasn't until that point in 2014 after having worked with
code for you know doing web development type thing, web design type things I started to
realize like I could actually use code to just make art and it wasn't really a clear
path at the moment but like I was starting to think about it and then over the course
of several years I just continued to try and move towards that but really it wasn't until
probably a few years ago that I started calling myself an artist and saying you know when
people ask me what I'm doing or if I'm going to some event and they're like you have to
put your job title in the badge or something like that it's like that's when I was finally
going to be okay this is what I want to do in life I just want to make art with code and
so I can start to put that on the event badge that says matilary artist and it's funny how
a light switches when you tell people that and when you tell yourself that you just sort
of you fall into it a bit more naturally so that was sort of yeah that was a turning
point I don't know the timing but a few years ago and since then I've just been now like
getting more and more like getting you know more and more entrenched into that sort of
idea of just making art and thankfully because of the NFT and crypto space it's really become
you know something where we a lot of artists we don't need to as much rely on some of the
you know web development web design type work that we were really focused on a lot in the
past now a lot of us can just make art and focus on that so yeah it's been an interesting
journey there.
And has your approach to making art changed due to NFTs I mean you've just mentioned it
NFTs have been life-changing for many artists because prior many of the artists like who
we know today and are really big in the NFT space and have creative work that's historically
relevant they have prior work is at agencies or have been doing web development or yeah
just had to have a job that helped them pay their rent and now there's NFTs and they're
sold by a marketplaces or platforms and even if it's called an exhibition in most cases
you know your work is mostly going to be seen on a website or on a smartphone so has that
change from what you've done prior creating work and the next step because with bright
moments or art blocks or yeah we now see many exhibitions happening so is that a difference
if you know okay you create a work that's mainly going to be seen online to okay I'm
creating work maybe immersive for an exhibition space is that a approach to you?
Yeah I think it's changed a lot of things in just the ways that I think we are all sort
of thinking about work a little bit so like even something like FX hash and I think a
platform like FX hash has sort of affected the way that a lot of generative artists are approaching
their work there's this sort of you know constant chatter about long-form generative art whereas
most of us were not really chatting about that or thinking about that type of workflow
where you spend months and months and months on a single script and that's your project
like a lot of us would have just been doing more like sketching with code and we would
have just been sort of sketching posting on Twitter posting on Instagram and then doing
a whole new sketch and not really doing anything with our work except you'd be posted and
then it just disappears and you know after it gets a few likes the next day it's kind
of gone and you're kind of forced to do more and like bring more content to these feeds
like Twitter or Instagram and that's kind of your you know way that's like what you're
forced to do in this sort of you know pre NFT type of generative artists posting on the
web posting on social media that's how at least I was feeling and I think some others
might have felt similar whereas now there's this kind of different workflow that exists
where we can really work towards a singular sort of vision or a singular idea or concept
or project and we cracked that and we build that out and at the end of it I mean it's
not you know guaranteed that it's going to do well or anything like that but at the
end of it there is something that you can release to the world that is more than just
a Twitter post that you know will get you 20 likes or something it might be an FX hash
post that gets you 20 Tezos but that's I mean 20 Tezos is not much but it's hell of a lot
better than just 20 likes and it's the kind of it's a different mindset there is like
instead of just posting for the social media for it to be disappeared you're posting on
these blockchains that are kind of permanent in a way and a lot of the work that you know
we have minted so far even many months later it's still being it's still very relevant
like it's it's amazing to see how that's changed as well like I don't really see some
of the you know pre-2021 generative harp really coming up over and over again in discussions
and things except for maybe like the really historical things whereas things that have
been minted there's this like kind of constant sharing of them and constant like revival
of them it's there's something to do with maybe the stewardship of them people want
to share what they've you know purchased and things like that whereas you know nobody's
re-sharing my like Twitter post from five years ago so it's just it's an interesting
new way of putting out this digital art in the world in a way that you know we were sort
of doing when whenever we would make a print or something like that we would put that that
thing out into the world and we would like give it to somebody and they would hold it
and cherish it and maybe share it with others but you know that's a physical way of distributing
work and now with NFTs we have this more digital or like digitally native way of distributing
work which is just ties a little bit more elegantly than saying oh the only way I can distribute
my work is as print which doesn't really make sense if you're a completely digital artist
it feels weird to force digital artists to work with a physical medium if they don't
want to kind of thing or if they don't feel it suits the work.
Thank you one quick thing for attendees you can ask your questions to the artists via
the hashtag on Twitter NFT Q&A or you can ask questions via discourse discourse we're
all happy to answer your questions.
I'll show you back I don't know if you've heard the question I guess you had a website
issues.
Yeah I just dropped for a second I think you have an idea of like the question but could
you repeat so the question was because Matt prior mentioned that his life has changed
or for many artists through NFTs because prior many of you worked at agencies or web developers
and then I was like and has creating work changed for you you first then started creating
work to be seen and shared and sold on marketplaces and platforms and now after the pandemic
we see more and more exhibitions happening immersive shows has it also now changed your
way of making art when you approach a project do you do it differently when you know okay
it's going to mainly live online or it's going to be in an exhibition and maybe even going
to be immersive.
I definitely have changed my life completely so where do I begin I think like every day
I wake up around 5 a.m. and I think I start I open up my program so once I was using
the day before I create something but before we had another motivation like Matt was saying
that before we're just sharing online and we didn't know what to do with all that work
and people were reacting to it and that was it but now we are able to create more time
and space to be creative by generating enough income to have all the space to experiment
to create projects to have the opportunity to be in galleries and now museums and I feel
that that's not only that wasn't my dream before I wasn't dreaming on being in a museum
when I started to interact with art it was like that's impossible I wasn't even thinking
about selling it I didn't even create it like print works or anything like that I was just
sharing online because I don't know I just wanted to get like an open diary a way to
express another language and that has been my way ever since I started with this in
2015. I also see it as a this is like a game an online game where a lot of people like
came into the launch of the game and like it was like the first few months of hype but
this existed before all of this hype like people were working on programs and on platforms
and ways to archive not only art but anything like any data on Shane and I think like the
game was on beta and then it switched to like a massive audience and this game has rewards
and items and people that love to collect things and put them in their house like if
and I think most people that are still in this are people that like games and that like
the the way it works like you create a community you walk around the server or the town and
you start just like what's what's new in it what's the new update but there's people
that are not in the game obviously those are that are refused to or not acknowledge but
to take the time to understand what happens in this game and there's some others that
are front end and they want to keep growing the space or what I would call like the server
where we live we're still a really small community in a sense.
So I think that's what keeps me not only motivated but it's more open to understanding
the dynamics so many things have changed if you notice like there's artists that have
more opportunities than others and I'm hopeful that by institutions or like the museums that
are approaching us or universities creating this venue is where we can talk about this
as a similar class it will attract more people into it and it will become more natural not
just an exclusive game where only a few have access to it.
That's the way like it had changed my family's life to like in real life I was just depending
on my mom and my brother for a long time because my mind could only focus on art and
I wasn't doing anything else.
I did work for a long time in tech support and you know so were hardware issues but I
never used a computer to create art and when I started doing it I couldn't stop and I
thanks to my family I was able to have the time to do this so yeah NFTs and the opportunities
that it opened up changed everything for me I always say it I'm always trying to like
come back and show gratitude because I didn't do it alone I wouldn't be here if it wasn't
for other people that are really interested in this and that wants to keep it going.
Thank you that's great to hear that NFTs really helped support you and your family
and yeah I think that's actually the best that could happen and I find it really interesting
that you said well you didn't even think about being in a museum and now institutions
approach you and I think that's very beautiful.
Helena how about you?
It's in terms of how NFT kind of changed my life I think like from the artistic perspective
it's mostly because I could stop being bucketed in the straight eye artist bucket I became
more kind of like digital artist and what it started very fruitful period in my art
making which I call post again is more post the I.R. where I kind of like could mix various
kind of like styles and things and people kind of responded to it and nobody kind of
required when I see the quite over 10 FTS nobody required for me making straight the
eye art so it kind of gave me like freedom and to kind of break through and to new angles
in my creativity so because from the money perspective to be honest I would have made
more money being a software consulting can be continuing to do this stuff so but yeah
I mean like Kickshail said when you start to making art you basically it's very hard
to switch back and forth I did it but but it's like for a long time but it's really
kind of hard to do but these days you basically kind of think about stuff is like stuff you
making new projects pretty much all the time and it helps when you have like several streams
because I'm not only like an artist I do a lot of like physical work like books and
stuff and I think it's very helpful like for artists not to be sort of like straight
and if it is all because I mean I think at least like in my case you need to have few
projects because maybe you failed in one but you will succeed in another one like selling
the books or making the books so it keeps you busy and keeps your creativity diversified
in a sense so because yeah I think like again I mean people can call themselves so whatever
but calling yourself and then the tea artist I think it's kind of limiting being an artist
and like make art try different things like stick with certain stuff but yeah I mean it
really kind of helpful to think this way and as you've just mentioned you work with AI
and I think over the past let's say six months we have seen a lot happening when it comes
to AI and artists or even non-artists using AI do you feel threatened by new technology
no I mean new technology kind of like I am using this technology and in a sense I think
like being a devil's advocate or kind of like contrarian I feel kind of like working with
GANS it's almost like working with obsolete technology and I welcome it because the at
the end of the day you need to do whatever kind of like makes you happy which makes interesting
things I mean technology is just like the tool I mean people you can use prompt based
AI you can use GANS you can use whatever like deep dream I mean as long as you kind of
create stuff that satisfies you and satisfies your audience that's what it is and artists
is basically a very kind of like loose definition if you call yourself the artist you're the
artist.
I mean what I'm oh sorry no go ahead I just wanted you know at the beginning of like
the wave of generative art that's saying I think it was 10,000,000,000,000 till 20,000
exploded but I think at the beginning people were doing a lot of perling noise circles
like it was just you can tell like they were just using repurposing someone else's like
projects and I think it's the same with AI like at the beginning you see a lot of like
really beautiful art but if you still if you see the same over and over again you can start
like realizing that like what's actually something that's out of the box that's different that
comes from an artist's mind you start curating that so I don't think we should be afraid
of like all this wave of new artists that use AI to create art like just like have to find
artists like Helena like create things that are really unique and comes from a very personal
place and like math and like many others so it's just about curation we're always going
to need curation no matter what comes new.
I mean also especially the three of you you all have found your voice and a signature
style might be the wrong word but I mean looking at your work it's quite clear it's coming
from you and I just got questions from the audience and one of the questions I always
also ask myself because I find it generous out I find really interesting I find it fascinating
like what Leander Hadswig and Richard Nadler have done for example with the Richter piece
you know that it's live running and I think yeah many people who started start collecting
or many younger artists who work with I don't know traditional medium think about well what
is a good way if you would like to start work with code or become generative artist and
I asked other artists to question myself well would I have a chance to learn coding these
day and someone like Travis Smalley the artist was doing the pixer rock set it took him like
five years and he basically taught himself how to code and some artists say to me it's
totally impossible don't even try it so what's your answer if someone says well how could
I get started even if I'm just interested in learning how to code and don't have the
goal of becoming an artist.
You might get easier soon with all the chat GPT and AI tools like GitHub co-pilot and
things I think as those things continue to develop it will become easier and easier to
use code for creating things and at a certain point it will maybe change where you know
the next wave of generative artists won't be really writing code by hand so much maybe
not maybe I don't know but maybe they'll be you know pulling on these AI systems to basically
help them synthesize maybe synthesize images but maybe also synthesize programs or some
sort of state machines or systems that then are used to drive some kind of our work but
I guess yeah to answer the question very simple other than using AI systems and hoping they
all continue to improve another way is just to do really simple things and I think simple
things are kind of under appreciated because there's this kind of constant drive to focus
on just the visual aesthetic and visual complexity and detail and things like that but I mean
simple things are kind of beautiful as well like Elsworth Kelly type shapes or of course
you know I'm always referencing solo it because the work is very simple and it's actually
something that is quite good for people that are kind of new to this to learn because
it's not like okay you need to implement like a crazy cellular autonomous type thing it's
something simpler and I know it's like the classic everyone talks about solo it type
thing but it is you know when you're using something as simple as a line or okay I have
a rectangle to draw because I don't want to spend five years learning how to code these
complex structures you know that's a source of inspiration so that's just my approach
to getting people interested in this and getting people to begin with this but I also recognize
that there's more than just solo it and then I know that's like a maybe contentious topic
because it's such an overused reference in this space but yeah yeah and then if kind
of like this a graphical geometrical stuff doesn't fascinate you or them maybe there
is no reason to learn I mean it's like I think it's a certain class of people who gets attracted
to generative art and like for me for example I came to know like processing and the cases
work back in 2010 but it didn't stick I mean I tried I could do stuff but because I was
a like professional social development it didn't work for me so that's why I kind of
like who found my game in the eye which is another kind of like mathematical approach
to art making or engineering so again find what you are for me and it's like there is
no kind of requirement to do the generative art right if you go to the agency yeah just
to follow up on that I mean there's others that are you know they like you're saying
they're not into the geometric and maybe they're not also into the AI and so they end
up going down a different path of like doing something analog but maybe leaving some sort
of generative system into it whether it's a computational or not or maybe they're doing
something you know with physical computing or with installation I think it's all sort
of it's very all tied together and you might end up finding that you prefer one of these
things over the other rather than just doing the sort of you know visual I don't know what
have we defined these things but like the visual geometric abstraction type generative
art as opposed to other areas that could also be described as generative art or computational
art algorithmic art or whatever.
Yeah for example I always wanted to create a game but and like something more complicated
than it's a team and imagine that in a few years we can or less than that we can create
like games on our own without the need of having like different kind of developers or
a big team or a big company to do so.
So those are the dreams.
I think with technology like this we can we can dream more like instead of being negative
negative about it we can think of way how to use it for good not just to you know just
to make quick money or copy others or being cool but there's so much more you can do
with it like research and like other fields will like exponentially get faster like instead
of years of like studying into like let's say a molecule like it will take less than
that and like there's so much so many uses for a side of art.
So yeah I'm pro. What is what would you say as an artist when you look at generative projects
of yourself and of other artists but it's what is a good project for you an interesting
project for you from yourself you continue working on and then actually publish and yeah
I guess that's the question.
What is good generative art after you when it comes to your own art and then to what
you collect or like our inspired by.
I guess that's a tricky one right.
There's I mean there's so many things where you see something and you just there's just
some some attachment to it and it's very personal and you can't always explain why you like
something and then there's other things where you might realize sort of that there's a lot
of work that's gone into something but it might not speak to you and it's I think it's
one of these tricky questions where it's like I don't know if I or anyone else is in
a position to be like that is not art or that is good art or that is bad art or or whatever
because I think it's just this it doesn't really seem to be a very effective thing and
I know that people become art critics and they some some art critics will just spend
a lot of their time focused on that question but it I don't know it's hard to say what's
good maybe attending exhibitions is a good way and also kind of like looking maybe for
clubs because I think like when two artists come together there is always something I
mean almost certain something interesting comes up like exactly Berman and this creville
each cover or myself with me three not to kind of like with myself on the shoulders
as so I think I like collapse like especially for independent artists is like really interesting
projects to look at.
So I think I missed your question.
I'll ask it again.
My question was what is good generative art for you?
How do you know what are criteria quality criteria when you look at other artists work
and when you look at your own work when do you know well this is a project you continue
working on yeah what is good for you what is interesting for you?
Oh the next one issues again.
Well we wait I could actually expand on that and I can just duck out when she's back but
for me I mean it's changed a lot in the last five years maybe I'll just I'll let okay
she's going in the notes so I'll just answer.
But for me it's changed a lot in the last five years because originally when I was learning
about generative art and and getting familiar with some of the sort of make ways of upcoming
things in generative art I was really looking up to sometimes like the very technical stuff
and I was like wow that's incredibly complex and like the way that this has been coded
is incredibly complex and I think nowadays I'm sort of more looking up to like the conceptual
stuff or the things that you know bring in outside maybe analog or bring in you know
sort of story or bring in these these things outside of just the complexity of code or
or the way that the sort of project was visually assembled and things like that so I don't
know that's just one comment.
Thank you.
I trust that having heard the question or was that a her cut off right or not?
Well I think people know that I was creating art online for a long time like in different
pages and my own page.
I just haven't a specific, not a specific but I just know what I like and I get obsessed
with it.
Like Matt says like sometimes when you are so obsessed or so into your own art you don't
really look into judging others like it just let it exist because like there's you know
different kind of trees out there.
So it's but when it comes to curating I think a theory of colors is very important like
the way you combine certain things, palettes, there's many generative artists that have
created like resources like palettes, color palettes for others to use and sometimes that's
you can see it around a lot like the same tones and colors and many many works but there's
art is that finds a way to create it like use it in a different way even if it's the
same palette that someone else shared.
I think that's been the center of generative art for a long time too like we all share
techniques and ways to do certain things and sometimes we find each other doing similar
works because it's all comes from algorithm and that just exists.
It's not something that someone invented.
So someone did discover and well math has its way to exist in like different forms in
nature and then in what we create.
So I think finding something that is different is the difficult part of all this like just
being able to trace back to everything you've seen before and understand.
We lost Ixrels again.
Yeah, I think we all agree that 16 minutes is how long we would like.
Oh, she's back.
We hear you again and see you again for it.
Oh, no.
Connection issues.
Yeah, so my last question would be because we said 16 minutes.
There's also questions from the audience.
The future of generative art and AI art.
I mean right now as all three of you also mentioned, we see a lot of sales but it seems
like a smaller community.
I think it feels like we all know each other.
Just maybe from Twitter or Discord or many of us have met at this point in time I think.
Yeah, and how do you see the future of the space and of generative art?
I mean we've seen the topic and I'm about at MoMA right now.
Oh, there she is.
Back again.
Hi.
Another try and then our last question.
I don't know if it's the internet or a server.
A string yard.
But yeah, where was I?
I think as I was saying, you'll have this certain unique taste for art.
For example, being at like really light colors, recently warm colors.
Before I was very into black and white only.
But at the same time I will create the same piece in different colors.
But I wouldn't show it.
Because I had this pattern of following same tones when I create a grid on my gallery,
which has been my Instagram page for a long time.
But yeah, it's just a matter of taste to discern and to turn out the art.
The other day I saw this meme about how perfect and adult art was like a lava lamp.
I just don't understand how you can reduce someone's creativity to just being part of
a room or entertainment.
There's so much more to it and so much work that goes behind.
But it's just the same with the internet.
You can find a lot of meaning in patterns that other people don't see or don't know
how to use them to say something.
I use the wave of the ocean, even photography or video or kinetic lines to express a lot.
So yeah, I think the way to generate the art is for the curator to actually fall in love
with what they're looking at and not just use as another object or another art to fill
up a gallery or whatever tasks they need to do.
For me, when you do everything with love, you can create a lot of magic.
When you don't do it, then you realize, oh, I was like automatic.
I was just acting like a robot.
Which surprisingly is something I try not to do.
I try to deep program myself all the time, one way or the other.
We lost our grandmother, I think her son is close to finish.
Great job.
Would you like to add something?
Oh, no.
She's saying she's just like an end of sentence.
Yeah.
I mean, she comes back for answering the last question because she also just mentioned
graphic anadol and yeah.
I mean, I think it's excellent for the piece base and for everyone of us to see graphic
anadol and normal.
And yeah, one of the attendees asked the question, where do we see the future of generative
art and I've just said prior, all of you also mentioned it sort of like it feels like
a small space because we somehow all know each other.
We have met in person or we know each other through Twitter or Discord.
So what's your prediction for the future?
Now, graphic anadol at MoMA.
I know that it's less speaking with a lot of institutions.
A lot of institutions have approached her.
And institution and then just collected the two NFTs from Leander Hatzog and Richard Nautla.
Gerhard and Richard are now in a museum collection.
So we see more and more NFTs going in.
Yeah, what's your prediction for the future?
Or what needs to happen that we see the future you hope for this space?
I could start, I guess.
I think there's sort of two questions and two answers here.
One of them is like, what's the future of NFTs?
And one of them is like, what's the future of generative art?
And I think they'll be both intertwined and linked in different ways.
But they'll also have different futures.
So the future, I think, of generative art is just sort of the continuation of it, except
expanding since like, you know, whatever the 60s or whenever we can say that it started
and just continuing to grow and expand in the public consciousness and hopefully grow
and expand in sort of the collections of the world in a way so that now we're starting
to see those artists be sort of acquired and be highlighted and be displayed.
But it's now beginning to happen over the course of the last couple of decades or something
like that.
And it will probably just continue to grow and there will be more and more interest in
maybe in 20 years.
It will be very common that a museum is going to be filled with digital art, which even
now it's still not exactly common.
You go to most of the world class museums or galleries and they're still not primarily
digital art, even though, you know, I think in as time goes on, we're living these sort
of very digital lives and we do have a lot of digital outputs and sometimes the ratio
of things don't really in current galleries don't really reflect the reality.
So that's one thing is just that it's going to continue to expand and grow and there'll
be different takes on a different ways of exploring that.
But then also I think with NFTs specifically, I think it will continue to like shift very,
very drastically.
I think the NFTs that we're seeing right now are like one type.
So like the reffic anodele in MoMA.
I think we will probably also continue to see museums and galleries, I mean, not that they
haven't already, but they will continue to have this focus on using the blockchain and
using these systems as like artistic mediums.
So I mean, the work of Ray and Myers or Deathbeef, I think those kind of artists will, you know,
be highlighted more and there will be more and more interest in building systems that
are using these kind of tools and using these kind of technologies.
Whereas sometimes there's a lot, there has been a lot of like mainstream focus and I
would count MoMA sort of as this mainstream sort of focus as well as like the NFT as an
image for the NFT as like a, as a gift for NFT animation or something.
But I don't think that's really the realistic future of NFTs.
I think they will be expanded to much more.
And I think it'll be pretty common that a lot of artists that work with digital and even
a lot of artists that work with physical will be distributing their work through these mechanisms,
even if they don't, you know, explicitly call them NFTs.
So just say I'm releasing some work and it's an auction, like right now I couldn't imagine
setting up my own auction with fiat.
I think it would be a disastrous nightmare where I was setting up an auction with crypto
is actually kind of makes sense.
Like you can have a Dutch auction with crypto and thousands of millions of people can participate
in it and you don't need to go to a single place like Christie's.
You can, you know, build these systems without going to Christie's or without going to Saudi
ways.
And you can direct how much percentage you want from the auction.
You don't need to subscribe to a 50% cut or something like that.
So I think it will just continue to grow and expand basically.
Helena, it's largest asked for your future prediction.
I think you're like in sync with Matt with what Matt said.
And honestly, I don't care much about being in museum or not being in museum.
I mean, I enjoy like the NFT gave artists the freedom to sell their stuff, to be shown
without kind of like institutions.
I haven't been to sort of this or anything, but kind of like, I don't feel miserable
because of this.
I mean, I kind of like create my own story.
So that's NFT again.
It's like about freedom and that's what I kind of like about it.
And I hope it continues like this.
I mean, we have enough kind of like tooling and infrastructure to make it happen with
independent collectors, with independent artists.
And that's the beauty of it.
I don't want to be in centralized honestly.
You know, from my perspective, I think it's an honor to be recognized by entities that
have been around for a long, long time and have managed to stay relevant.
We lost I excels again.
You're back.
Beautiful.
So before I'm misunderstood, what I'm trying to say is that NFT is definitely or like blockchain
art is a revolution.
It's a way for us to create our own museums.
Like we are actually moving up to long ago about how it was called like, but also Tranquilidad
Agasso program sale, which means for your tranquility, do your own museum.
For some people, being a museum is not about just the recognition that it's about preserving.
I will literally just disappear if my art disappears.
I don't think I could stand that.
And if we keep it in an unstable place, like it's a web browser or Instagram, like it certainly
carries that risk.
I think one of my biggest goals is to preserve myself through time regardless if I'm here
or not.
So that's one of the reasons why I enjoy or I respect the fact that museums are paying
attention to this.
We lost her again.
That's what a few seconds and then, no, she's back.
She's always coming back.
That's the good thing we know by now.
It's very reliable.
I shall be coming back.
Or maybe not this time around.
I mean, the good thing is you all know where to find us on Twitter and on Discord.
So if you have further questions, please just send them to us via Twitter.
We're happy to answer.
Thank you, Matt, Helena, and I excels for being with me here and discussing generative
art and thank you for the audience and for your great questions.
Please get in touch with us.
Thank you.
Bye.